<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Worcesters apophthegmes or witty sayings of the Right Honourable Henry (late) Marquess and Earl of Worcester, delivered upon severall occasions, and now published for the benefit of the reader. By T.B. a constant observer, and no lesse admirer of his Lordships wisdom and loyalty.</title>
            <author>Worcester, Henry Somerset, Marquis of, 1577-1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1650</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 135 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 63 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96909</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3535</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1350_2</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R204142</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863831</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863831</idno>
            <idno type="VID">116046</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96909)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 116046)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 178:E1350[2])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Worcesters apophthegmes or witty sayings of the Right Honourable Henry (late) Marquess and Earl of Worcester, delivered upon severall occasions, and now published for the benefit of the reader. By T.B. a constant observer, and no lesse admirer of his Lordships wisdom and loyalty.</title>
                  <author>Worcester, Henry Somerset, Marquis of, 1577-1646.</author>
                  <author>Bayly, Thomas, d. 1657?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 114 p., plate   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J. Clowes, for Edward Blackmore, at the Angell in Pauls Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1650.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: Thomas Bayly.</note>
                  <note>The "plate" is a woodcut.</note>
                  <note>Variant: title begins: Worcesters apophthegme.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June 29".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Aphorisms and apothegms --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Geremy Carnes</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:116046:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>woodcut of three men surrounding the scales of reason</figDesc>
                  <p>sdom. manus Prouidentia. Iudgement Reason dependency Vild Rerum Precius Viceſſitudo</p>
               </figure>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:116046:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> WORCESTERS APOPHTHEGMES.</p>
            <p>OR WITTY SAYINGS OF THE Right Honourable HENRY (late) Marqueſs and Earl of WORCESTER, Delivered upon ſeverall occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, and now Publiſhed for the benefit of the READER.</p>
            <p>By <hi>T. B.</hi> a conſtant obſerver, and no leſſe admirer of his Lordſhips Wiſdom and Loyalty.</p>
            <p>Et prodeſſe volunt et delectare.</p>
            <p>LONDON. Printed by <hi>J. Clowes,</hi> for <hi>Edward Blackmore,</hi> at the <hi>Angell</hi> in <hi>Pauls</hi> Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, 1650.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:116046:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:116046:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:116046:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To the Right Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable EDWARD, Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe and Earle of WORCES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TER and GLAMORGAN, Baron of</hi> Chepston, <hi>Viſcount</hi> Groſſmount <hi>and</hi> Caldicott, <hi>my very Honourable</hi> Lord.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My very good Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e many favours, which I received from your <hi>Noble</hi> Family, eſpecially, from your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rought, upon a diſpoſition, <hi>ſome-deale</hi> a pretender unto gratitude, how it might in <hi>ſome meaſure,</hi> or other, anſwer the reſpect, and <hi>cleare</hi> the heart, that had layen charg'd ſo long, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th <hi>benefits;</hi> but it found no meanes but (onely thus) to let your Honour ſee, that the favours which were conferr'd upon me: were not <hi>ſpilt,</hi> but <hi>powred</hi> into a <hi>Violl,</hi> that (what it hath received and containes, bears <hi>Paper</hi> of acknowledgment, and
<pb facs="tcp:116046:4"/> that, neither the diſtances of <hi>Time,</hi> nor <hi>Place,</hi> nor all the <hi>(Left-handed)</hi> ſtroaks of fortune, which have lately fallen ſo <hi>heavily,</hi> upon your <hi>Illuſtrious</hi> Family, ſhall ever be able, to beat down a reſpect, that <hi>emulates</hi> the Cypreſſe which bears <hi>up</hi> (ſtill) in growth maugre the <hi>heavy weights,</hi> which the hand of fate (ignorant of its virtue) hath ſo <hi>hung,</hi> on all her branches. <hi>My Lord,</hi> it may be it will not be unpleaſing to your <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> to <hi>read</hi> your Father, <hi>ſpeaking</hi> after death; eſpecially, when you read him, <hi>dying,</hi> with ſuch <hi>ſpeeches</hi> in his mouth. I layd your Noble Father in his grave, with my <hi>own hands,</hi> but I could not let ſuch a memoriall of him, lye <hi>buried,</hi> under my own <hi>Manuſcript;</hi> but thought it a <hi>du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> belonging to <hi>his</hi> fame, and <hi>your</hi> merit, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate this book unto your <hi>Lordſhip, Heir</hi> to <hi>all:</hi> but <hi>apparently</hi> to <hi>nothing,</hi> but <hi>his</hi> virtues, and <hi>this</hi> memoriall of them; which in all humility, (together with my ſelf) I proſtrate at your feet; who think it the greateſt honour, ſtill to be owned,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Lordſhips humble, and faithfull Servant THOMAS BAYLY</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="author_to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:116046:4"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE <hi>READER.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>HAving lately publiſhed a private Diſcourſe concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Religion, between the late King, and the Marqueſs of <hi>Worceſter</hi> in <hi>Raglan</hi> Caſtle, as alſo certain papers which went ſo between them; and this in juſtification of the late Kings conſtant affection to the Proteſtant Religion, which hath been much oppugned by divers, both before, and after his death; yet, I hear there are ſome, who pretend to love and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the memory of the dead King, and glory, in the relation of being ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants to his late Majeſty, that will not admit of that controverſie, otherwiſe then as a parable: Firſt, becauſe they were there, &amp; heard of no ſuch thing. Secondly, becauſe they believed not
<pb facs="tcp:116046:5"/> the Marqueſſe of <hi>Worceſter</hi> to have been ſo able a man, and as I heare, it hath been ſaid ſo by ſome of his Majeſties field-Chaplains; who en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vying that a loyall pen ſhould wagge, where they can be contented to ſow pillowes under the elbowes, to beat cuſhions over the heads of a people (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt whom ſhaking the duſt from off their feet, as a witneſſe againſt them, had ſeem'd more like an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall imitation then preaching to them.) And preach ſuch wholeſom and ſound Doctrine of Mortification, Sanctification, Juſtification, and Good life, that they thought they might ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly get up into any Pulpit, not ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring what bottome it had, nor what canopie was over head, not much un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like the man who went to ſearch after the ſureneſſe of the foundation, when his houſe was all on fire. Theſe men will tell you that this was no reall thing, becauſe they were there all the while, whileſt they were not there at all, except at meales; and when, I
<pb facs="tcp:116046:5"/> tell you that they were the Doctours that were better at ſmelling out a good dinner, then a diſputation; I have as good as told you their names. I expected better reaſon from thoſe Doctours, then from the Knight that ſaid he was ſure there ſhould be no ſuch thing at <hi>Raglan,</hi> for his boy <hi>Tom</hi> was there all the time; as if the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of <hi>Worceſter</hi> could not watch his opportunity in a moneths time to have two hours private Diſcourſe with the King, while he was in his own houſe, but al the Caſtle muſt take notice of it, or that papers might not paſs between them, but all the world muſt know it.</p>
            <p>But you will ſay, you do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve that there was any ſuch private diſcourſe. Chuſe then, who cares? let him believe it that will; it was writ for ſatisfaction of Chriſtians, not infidels. But it may be <hi>Mendax fama</hi> meanes to require me for the wrong ſhe did my father, who writ a good book, and ſome would not
<pb facs="tcp:116046:6"/> believe it to be his; and now I have ſet out a book, as none of mine own, and ſhe will have it to be mine. I thank her kindly, but I had rather be without her praiſes, then to be thought ſuch an ingenious lyar. As to the objection of the Marqueſſes inability to talke ſo to the King, I ſhall aſſure you by his Apophthegmes in this book [which I never had the leaſt thought to have publiſhed but upon this occaſion] that he uſed to talk ſo wiſely, that all the wiſdome that I had thought them worthy of record, and [now] of publication. To a great many of which ſayings, there are a great many witneſſes to juſtifie a truth that cannot be denied, and muſt needs verifie the former: and ſo Good morrow, or Good evening to you, according unto the time of the day that the book lighted into your hands, I am</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your ſervant <hi>Tho. Bayley</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="collection">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:116046:6"/>
            <head>WORCESTERS <hi>APOPHTHEGMES.</hi>
            </head>
            <div n="1" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt time that ever I had the hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs to be acquainted with this <hi>Noble-man,</hi> was by accident, upon the <hi>Welch</hi> Mountains: where I met him, flying a danger with a ſofter pace then it made after him: whoſe condition ſo dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous, was the more deſperate, becauſe he was unſenſible of the approach of any Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my, and his ſecurity the ſooner wrought, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe Intelligence had not given the enemy any Information, how near they were unto him: it was my fortune, firſt to inform my ſelf, and then his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> of the one, &amp; after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:116046:7"/> his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> of the other particular, as alſo of the rub that I had caſt in the way, that had turn'd aſide the Bowle that was running ſo fairely towards the mark. After that I had told him all the particulars of what I had done, and what I further meant to do, in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to his preſervation with a compoſed countenance, wherein you might read, not the leaſt perturbation of mind: he gave me this Language: <hi>Sir, it is fit that you ſhould have your reward, I am yours: and</hi> (imbracing me ſaid.) <hi>Now I put you in full poſſeſſion of your own, I pray diſpoſe of me as you pleaſe:</hi> from which time forward untill the time that I laid him in his grave in <hi>Windſor</hi> Caſtle, I never parted from him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. 2.</head>
               <p>ABout the ſame time recovering the top of an high Mountain, by the advantage of the ground, we could ſee the Enemy marching another way; at which ſight, the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:116046:7"/> 
                  <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> dwelt with his eyes a little longer upon that Object. The Lord <hi>John Somerſet</hi> (his Sonne) thought convenient: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> made his reply. <hi>O Sonne, I love to ſee mine own danger, eſpecially when it is marching off.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. 3.</head>
               <p>AFter that my endeavours were crowned with ſucceſſe, and my diligence had wrought his ſecurity, in a place that was as private as he had made himſelf; having part<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with all his retinue, we began to commune with our ſelves, concerning our own happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs; and ſome there were who told his <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> that though the place were unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of him, yet it was better then a priſon: to which the <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> made this anſwer. <hi>It may be not: It may be my ſinnes did not deſerve ſo great a favour, for that is alwayes better which God ſends.</hi> To which I had a Siſter, which was Mrs. of the houſe who thus replied unto
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:116046:8"/> him: then ſure (my Lord) this is beſt, for God hath ſent you hither. <hi>But Lady,</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſſe,) <hi>it had not been beſt, if God had diſpoſed of me otherwiſe: why ſhould we repine at that freedom of the Almighty over us, which we daily exerciſe over other Creatures? We im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſon harmleſs Creatures, and innocent Birds, within Cages, onely to ſing to us and make us me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody, and why ſhould I do otherwiſe then ſubmit unto the will of God, if it ſhould be his pleaſure to make me a cloſe Priſoner, ſeeing he may delight in hearing, how prittily I would complain?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. 4.</head>
               <p>I Have lived in <hi>Ragland</hi> Caſtle, 3 years, and in all that time, I never ſaw man drunk, nor heard an Oath, amongſt any, of all his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants: neither did I ever ſee a better ordered Family, and that which is moſt wonderfull unto me, was, the Servants of his houſe, (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing half Papiſts, and half Proteſtants) were never at variance, in point of Religion: which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:116046:8"/> was brought about, by prohibiting diſputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: neither was any man the leſſe accepted for his Religion, if his ſervice were acceptable; but when the Caſtle was fill'd with Officers, and Souldiers, he uſ'd to be much grieved, to hear, and ſee the Oaths, and drunkenneſſe, that was (then and there) too much practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: inſomuch, that when ſome of his chief Officers, had told him, how that they had fortified ſuch and ſuch a place, ſo and ſo: and that here the Enemy could not come, and there it was impoſſible; <hi>I but</hi> (ſaid my Lord) <hi>you have left the main place open, and unfortified: you have made no fortifications againſt Heaven; for there is ſuch ſwearing, and drunkenneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt you, that I fear me that from thence will come your greateſt enemy; and you have made no proviſion againſt him.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. 5.</head>
               <p>WHen the <hi>King</hi> had made his repaire to <hi>Raglan,</hi> after the Battell of <hi>Naſby,</hi> taking occaſion to thank the <hi>Marqueſs</hi> for
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:116046:9"/> ſome monies lent his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> the <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> return'd his <hi>Majeſty</hi> this anſwer: <hi>Sir, I had your word for my mony; but I never thought I ſhould be ſo ſoone repaid, for now you have given me thanks, I have all I look for.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. 6.</head>
               <p>ANother time, the <hi>King</hi> came unto my <hi>Lord,</hi> and told him, that he thought not to have ſtay'd with his <hi>Lordſhip,</hi> above three dayes, but his occaſions requiring his longer abode with him, he was willing to eaſe him of ſo great a burthen, as to be altogether ſo heavy a charge unto him. And conſidering it was a Gariſon, that his proviſions might not be ſpent by ſo great a preſſure, he was willing that his <hi>Lordſhip</hi> ſhould have power given him, to take what Proviſions the Countrey would afford, for his preſent maintenance, and recruit: to which his Lordſhip made this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply. <hi>I humbly thank your Majeſty, but my Caſtle will neither ſtand long, if it leanes upon the</hi>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:116046:9"/> 
                  <hi>Countrey. I had rather be brought to a morſell of bread, then any morſels of bread ſhould be brought me, to entertain your Majeſty.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. 7.</head>
               <p>SIr, <hi>Henry Bard,</hi> who was Lord <hi>Bellamount,</hi> coming into the Hall at <hi>Raglan,</hi> and ſeeing ſo many Tables furniſhed with food, and feeders, ſwore a great Oath, that the <hi>King</hi> had a plot to deſtroy that Family. Firſt, in borrowing all the old mans mony: and then in coming (thus) to eat up his victuals; which being told unto the Marqueſſe, the Marqueſſe asked the man (who made this Relation unto him) of what Gariſon the Lord <hi>Bellamount</hi> was Governour: it was told his Lordſhip that he was Governour of <hi>Camb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> houſe: the <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> replyed, <hi>That when the King had done as he ſaid, that then his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty might go to his Gariſon, and there he might have Cambdens remaines.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:116046:10"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. 8.</head>
               <p>WHen the <hi>King</hi> firſt entred the Caſtle of <hi>Raglan,</hi> the <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> kiſſ'd the <hi>Kings</hi> hand, and riſing up again, he ſaluted his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> with this Complement, <hi>Domine non ſum dignus.</hi> The King replyed unto the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe. <hi>My Lord I may very well anſwer you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, I have not found ſo great faith in Iſrael; for no man would truſt me with ſo much money as you have done:</hi> To which the Marqueſſe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, <hi>I hope your Majeſty will prove a defender of the Faith.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. 9.</head>
               <p>SIr <hi>Thomas Somerſet,</hi> brother to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe, had a houſe which they called <hi>Troy,</hi> within five miles of <hi>Raglan</hi> Caſtle: this
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:116046:10"/> Sir <hi>Thomas Somerſet</hi> being a neate man, both within, and without his houſe, as he was a compleat Gentleman of himſelf, every way delighted very much in fine Gardens, and Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chards, and in repleniſhing and ordering them with all the varieties of choiſeſt fruits, that could be got: and in defending his new Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations from the coldneſſe of the climate, by the benefit of art; the earth that was ſo much made of, prov'd ſo gratefull to him, at the ſame time that the <hi>King</hi> happened to be at his Brothers houſe at <hi>Raglan:</hi> that it yield<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him wherewithall to ſend his Brother <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> ſuch a preſent, as at that time of year and place was able to make the <hi>King,</hi> and all his Lords believe, that the Soveraign of the Planets, with all his Prince Electors, had new chang'd the Poles: and that <hi>Wales</hi> the reffuſe, and out-caſt of the faire Garden of <hi>England</hi> had fairer and riper fruit, growing upon her ſtone rubbiſh, then <hi>Englands</hi> levels, had on all her beds: this, preſented to the Marqueſſe, the Marqueſſe would not ſuffer to be preſented to the <hi>King,</hi> by any other hands, except his own. In comes the Marqueſſe to the <hi>King,</hi> at the latter end of ſupper, led by the arme, having ſuch a goodly preſence with him, that his being led, became him, rather
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:116046:11"/> like ſome ceremony of ſtate, then ſhow of impotence: and his ſlow pace, (occaſioned by his infirmity) expreſs'd a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> gravity, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then feebleneſs: thus (with a ſilver diſh in each hand, fill'd with rarities, and a little basket upon his arme, as a ſupply, in caſe his Majeſty ſhould be over-bountifull of his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours to the Ladies that were ſtanders by.) He makes his third obeyſance, and thus ſpeakes. <hi>May it pleaſe your Majeſty, if the</hi> 4 <hi>Elements could have been rob'd to have entertain'd your Majeſty, I think I had but done my duty; but I muſt do as I may. If I had ſent to Briſtoll for ſome good things, to entertain your Majeſty, that had been no wonder at all: If I had procured from</hi> London, <hi>ſome goodneſſe, that might have been acceptable to your Majeſty, that had been no wonder indeed. But here I preſent your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> (placing his diſhes upon the Table) <hi>with what neither came from</hi> Lincoln <hi>that was, nor</hi> London <hi>that is: nor</hi> York<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>that is to be; but I aſſure your Majeſty, that this Preſent came from</hi> Troy: whereupon the King ſmil'd, and anſwered the Marqueſſe, <hi>truly my Lord,</hi> I <hi>have heard, that Corne now growes where</hi> Troy <hi>Town ſtood; but</hi> I <hi>never thought there had growen a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny</hi> Apricocks <hi>there before.</hi> Whereupon the Marqueſſe replyed. <hi>Any thing to pleaſe your</hi>
                  <pb n="11" facs="tcp:116046:11"/> 
                  <hi>Majeſty.</hi> The fruit was very much admired by all, and it was acknowledged by all that were in the preſence at that time, that they never ſaw the <hi>King</hi> ſerv'd in greater ſtate in all their lives. There were ſome about the <hi>King,</hi> who followed my Lord Marqueſſe, when he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted the preſence, and told his Lordſhip, that he would make a very good Courtier. I (ſaid the Marqueſs) I <hi>remember</hi> I <hi>ſaid one thing that may give you ſome hopes of me.</hi> Any thing to pleaſe your <hi>Majeſty.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. 10.</head>
               <p>THe firſt night his <hi>Majeſty</hi> came unto the Caſtle, the <hi>King</hi> deſired to ſee the great Tower, which was the place where his Lordſhip did uſe to keep his Treaſure: His Majeſty ſpake unto me to fetch the Keyes. I ran down to the <hi>Marqueſs,</hi> and acquainted him with the <hi>Kings</hi> pleaſure, who would needes bring them to the <hi>King,</hi> and ſhew him the Tower himſelf; when the <hi>King</hi> ſaw the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:116046:12"/> 
                  <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> bringing the Keyes himſelf, he thus ſpake unto the Marqueſs. <hi>My Lord, there are ſome men, who are ſo unreaſonable, as to make me believe, that your Lordſhip hath good ſtore of gold yet left within this Tower; but</hi> I <hi>knowing how</hi> I <hi>have exhauſted you, (together, with your own occaſions) could never have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved it, untill now</hi> I <hi>ſee you will not truſt the Keyes with any Lady but your ſelf:</hi> To which the Marqueſs made this reply. <hi>Sir,</hi> I <hi>was ſo farre from giving your Majeſty any ſuch occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of thought by this tender of my duty, that</hi> I <hi>proteſt unto you, that</hi> I <hi>was once reſolved that your Majeſty ſhould have layen there, but that</hi> I <hi>was loath to commit your Majeſty to the Tower.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. 11.</head>
               <p>THere was a poor Free-holder, who had a ſmall Tenement, cloſe underneath <hi>Rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> Caſtle, in value about ſix pounds, <hi>per An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num:</hi> the <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> had a mind to buy it of the owner, it lying within his land, and ſo
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:116046:12"/> near unto his Caſtle: treating with the owner about it, he found him extreamly averſe from hearkening to any conditions whatſoever: the <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> (hereupon) told the man, that he made not any ſuch propoſition out of any evill intention towards him, but to his great advantage; for he would give him ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teene pounds <hi>per Annum,</hi> in any place of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> or <hi>Wales,</hi> where he had any <hi>Land,</hi> or op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to purchaſe ſuch an inheritance for him; but the man remained obſtinate, tell<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the <hi>Marqueſſe,</hi> that he would not looſe the ſight of ſo goodly a Caſtle as <hi>Raglan,</hi> for tenne pounds <hi>per Annum:</hi> this conſtrued (as indeed it was) an Anſwer no leſſe peeviſh then inſolent: the Marqueſs told him that he would ſpoile his proſpect, and ſo diſmiſſ'd him, cauſing (forthwith) a double rowe of Trees, which ſhould (in time) take away two thirds of the Revenue, which ſhould accrew out of the poor mans eyes. The <hi>Kings</hi> coming to <hi>Raglan,</hi> being at the time when theſe Trees were grown to their height, when the tall Ceder of our Lebanus, was brought ſo low, and thoſe Sycamores flouriſhed, when the royal Oake was in the fall of the leafe; It happened that his Majeſty was at bowles up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on <hi>Raglan</hi> Caſtle Green (a place ſo proudly
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:116046:13"/> ſcituated, that you might as well com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand all the Countrey, round about with your eye, as the Lord thereof the Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men by his power and authority, where you might find a goodly proſpect without looſing your own eyes,) where after that he had en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded his recreation, his Majeſty was pleaſed to delight himſelf, which obſerving the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey round about: It happened, that one <hi>Pritchard,</hi> the <hi>Kings</hi> Partner at Bowles (whoſe unmannerlineſſe had informed him that Bowles had the ſame virtue in them, that the Foot-balls had, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to make all fellowes, preſuming more upon his good bowling, then good manners continued the familiarity that ſhould have ended with the rubbers, ſhewing the <hi>King</hi> where his houſe ſtood ſome three miles off, and told his Majeſty that he muſt look through the wood, and he might ſee a white thing, and that was it; moreover, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainting his Majeſty what the Lord of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> had adviſed him <hi>(viz.)</hi> to cut down ſome of thoſe Trees, that the houſe might be plainly diſcern'd from the Green, whereby his Lordſhip when he wanted a good Bowler, might make a ſigne, and ſo have him at a beck: To which the <hi>King</hi> replyed. Mr. <hi>Pritch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ard,</hi> let me give you better advice: put up
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:116046:13"/> more Trees, where the Trees are ſo thin, that my Lord of <hi>Worceſter</hi> (if it be poſſible) may not ſee thy houſe at all. The <hi>Marqueſſe</hi> of <hi>Worceſter</hi> ſuppoſing the <hi>King</hi> had touch't up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on this greedineſs of purchaſing all the Land which was near unto him, ſhewed His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty the Rowes of Trees, and told the <hi>King</hi> that beyond thoſe Trees ſtood a pritty Tene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nement, and becauſe he would not have <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boths</hi> Vineyard to be an eye-ſore to him, he had planted thoſe trees to hood-winck his eyes from ſuch temptations; whether the <hi>King</hi> had heard of it before or no, I cannot tell, but his Majeſty happened to light upon the true cauſe of their ſetting up: telling his Lordſhip, <hi>that he was as conceited in the ſetting up thoſe Trees as his Father was witty in cutting down the great Wall-nut-tree,</hi> which the Earl of <hi>Salisbury,</hi> gave an hundred pounds to my Lord of <hi>Worceſters</hi> man to perſwade his Lordſhip to cut it down, becauſe it hindred his proſpect towards the Thames, but being cut down, the Earl of <hi>Worceſter</hi> ſet up ſuch a houſe in the place thereof, that <hi>Salisbury</hi> that way could not ſee the Thames at all. Whereupon my Lord of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> ſaid that the <hi>Earl of Salisbury would be even with him, for he was afraid that he would pull down his</hi>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:116046:14"/> 
                  <hi>houſe ere it be long:</hi> to which the <hi>King</hi> made anſwer, <hi>that when the time came that he durſt pull down his houſe, he and ſuch as he, would pull an old houſe over their own head;</hi> the Marqueſſe replyed, <hi>if they will make ſo bold with their own heads, I will give them leave to be ſo bold with a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of my houſes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. 12.</head>
               <p>WHen the <hi>King</hi> firſt entred the Gates of <hi>Raglan,</hi> the Marqueſſe delivered his Majeſty the keyes, (according to the odinary Cuſtome) the <hi>King</hi> reſtoring of them to the Marq; the Marq; ſaid, I <hi>beſeech your Maj. to keep them, if you pleaſe, for they are in a good hand; but</hi> I <hi>am afraid that ere it be long,</hi> I <hi>ſhall be forc'd to deliver them into the hands of thoſe who will ſpoile the Complement.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:116046:14"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. 13.</head>
               <p>AT the <hi>Kings</hi> being at <hi>Raglan,</hi> there were ſome informations given, of ſome Gentlemen of the Country, who were ſuppoſed (and not without cauſe) to have done his Majeſty many ill Offices, by with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawing the hearts of the People from his Majeſty, and obſtructing many aydes, and aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtances, which otherwiſe his Majeſty was like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to have had out of theſe parts: theſe men (being thus accuſed) were ordered to be laid hold on, and it was executed accordingly, and they being brought before his Majeſty, it was moved by ſome, that they ſhould be forth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with tryed by a Commiſſion of <hi>Oyer</hi> and <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miner;</hi> others adviſed his <hi>Majeſty,</hi> that they ſhould be ſent to <hi>Hereford,</hi> and there to be kept in ſafe Cuſtody, untill further conſultati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons might be had concerning them, they ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſing themſelves as well as they could. One of them proteſting his innocence with teares in his eyes, the <hi>King</hi> ordered that he ſhould
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:116046:15"/> forthwith be releaſed, being alwayes prone to leane to mercy rather then juſtice, and to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable, rather then rigid conſtruction of his very enemies. The King, coming back from <hi>Abergaveny,</hi> where this was put in execution, The King told the Marqueſſe what he had done, and that when he ſaw them ſpeak ſo honeſtly, he could not but give ſome credit to their words, ſo ſeconded by tears; and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all, told the Marqueſſe, that he had onely ſent them to priſon; whereupon the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe ſaid, <hi>what to do, to poyſon that Gariſon?</hi> Sir, <hi>you ſhould have done well to have heard their accuſations, and then to have ſhewed what mercy you pleaſ'd.</hi> The King told him, <hi>that he heard that they were ac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſed by ſome contrary faction, as to themſelves, who out of the diſtaſte they bore to one or other upon old grudges, would be apt to charge them more home, then the nature of their offences had deſerved;</hi> to whom the Marqueſs made this return, <hi>well Sir, you may chance to gaine you the Kingdom of Heaven by ſuch do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings as theſe; but if ever you get the Kingdom of</hi> England <hi>by theſe tricks, I'le be your Bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:116046:15"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. 14.</head>
               <p>THe Marqueſs had a mind to tell the <hi>King</hi> (as handſomely as he could) of ſome of his (as he thought) faults, and thus he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trives his plot, againſt the time that his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty was wont to give his Lordſhip a viſit, as commonly he uſ'd to do after dinner, his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip had the book of <hi>John Gower,</hi> lying be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him on the Table. The King caſting his eye upon the book, told the Marqueſs that he had never ſeen it before. O ſaid the Marqueſs, <hi>it is the book of books, which if your Majeſty had been well verſ'd in, it would have made you a King of Kings.</hi> Why ſo my Lord? ſaid the King, why ſaid the Marqueſs, here is ſet down how <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> brought up, and inſtructed <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexander</hi> the great in all the rudiments, and principles, belonging to a Prince, and under the perſons of <hi>Alexander</hi> and <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> he read the King ſuch a leſſon, that all the ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders by were amazed at the boldneſs; and the King ſuppoſing that he had gone further
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:116046:16"/> then his Text would have given him leave: asked the Marq; if he had his leſſon by heart, or whether he ſpake out of the book: the Marqueſs replyed, <hi>Sir, if you could read my heart, it may be you might find it then. Or if your Majeſty pleaſe to get it by heart, I will lend you my book:</hi> which latter profer, the King ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed of, and did borrow it; nay ſaid the <hi>Marqueſs,</hi> I will lend it you upon theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, firſt, that you read it, ſecondly, that you make uſe of it; but perceiving how that ſome of the new made Lords, fretted and bit their thumbs at certain paſſages in the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſes diſcourſe, he thought a little to pleaſe his Majeſty, though he pleaſ'd them the men, who were ſo much diſpleaſed allready, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſting unto his Majeſty, that no man was ſo much for the abſolute power of a King: as <hi>Ariſtotle,</hi> deſiring the book out of the Kings hand, he told the King, that he would ſhew him one remarkable paſſage to that purpoſe, turning to that place that had this verſe, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A King can kill, a King can ſave,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>A King can make, a Lord a knave,</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>And of a knave, a Lord alſo,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
               </q>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:116046:16"/>
               <p> Whereupon there were divers new made Lords, who ſlunk out of the roome, which the King obſerving, told the Marqueſs, <hi>my Lord at this rate you'l drive away all my Nobility,</hi> the Marqueſſe replyed, <hi>I proteſt unto your Majeſty, I am as new a made Lord as any of them all, but I was never call'd knave and rogue, ſo much in all my life, as I have been ſince I received this laſt Honour, and why ſhould not they bear their ſhares?</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. 15.</head>
               <p>AS the Marqueſs was in his travel from <hi>Denbyſhire</hi> (where he had layen con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceal'd ſome while) towards <hi>Raglan,</hi> we had determined to lodge in a poor Town called <hi>Bala,</hi> in <hi>Merionethſhire,</hi> the Marqueſs being invited to take ſome repoſe, at one Mr. <hi>Owen Salisbury</hi> of <hi>Keeg,</hi> I and one more, went be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to provide accomodation for his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip in that Town, where we found that ſome had plaid the knave with us, and had infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med the Tovvn, that about ſuch a time there
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:116046:17"/> would come a party of the enemy through the Town; the Townſmen neither being pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared nor able to make any reſiſtance, nor willing to harbour any ſuch gueſts, were ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry much divided and confounded in their couſultations, but ſeeing none but two Horſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men coming towards the Town, they admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted us in, but not without ſome ſuſpition, and many ſcores of men, women, and Children, following us at our heeles, whereſoever we went, we marvelled very much at them, and they at us: we went into ſeveral poor Innes, and we were told every where there was no lodging for us; I inquired for the Maior of the Town, he was not to be ſpoken with, I inquired after the Deputy Governour of the place, or any Officer, but cold not come to the ſpeech of any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the multitude increaſed, ſo did our wonders; at the laſt I ſpide a young man, who had a ribbin in his hat, with <hi>vive la Roy</hi> in it: I applyed my ſelf to him, and told him that he by his <hi>favour</hi> ſhould be one that loved the King, and that there was ſuch a Nobleman who had ſerv'd the King in no ſmall meaſure, who was likely to lie in their ſtreetes for want of a lodging: the young man ſhewed me (forthwith) great reſpect, telling me that his Lordſhip ſhould be very
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:116046:17"/> welcome to his Mothers houſe: vvho kept a poor Inne, &amp; withall told us the reaſon of the peoples ſhieneſſe to harbour us, as aforeſaid, vve vvent into the houſe, finding it a moſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable receptacle for ſuch a perſon; but yet better then none at all, the parlour where my Lord was to lie, was a ſoft and looſe ground, wherein you might ſink up to the anckles every ſtep, the top of the houſe being thatched with ill-threſhed ſtraw, the Corne that was left in the ſtraw vvhere with the houſe was thatched; grew, &amp; vvas all as green as graſſe: the Marques (by that time that we had got a good fire, and had laid ſome looſe boards, and ſtrawed the new made floar with ruſhes) came into the Town, and ſeeing the manner of the houſe-top, and the parlour bottome, ſaid, <hi>That he lay over a Bogge, and under a Meddow.</hi> But it being known vvho he vvas, the Maior of the Town, vvith ſingular reſpect, and much humanity came unto the Marqueſs, and excuſed the rudeneſſe of the Tovvnſmen, and ſhevved his Lordſhip the miſtake, offering his Lordſhip his ovvn houſe, and many other civilities, and vvhat elſe his Lordſhip thought might lie vvithin his povver; for vvhich my Lord gave him many and hearty thanks, breaking out into this
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:116046:18"/> Meditation. <hi>Lord what a thing this miſunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, I warrant you: might but the Kign and the Parliament conferre together, as you and I have done, there might be as right an under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding betwixt them, as there is now between you and I; ſome body have told the Parliament, that the King was an enemy, &amp; their believing of him to be ſuch, hath wrought all the jealouſies which are come to theſe diſtractions, the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment being now in ſuch a caſe as I my ſelf am, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving green eares over their heads, and falſe ground under their feet.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. 16.</head>
               <p>IN the ſame Town (at my Lords departure) by the careleſneſſe of his Servants, 1000<hi>l.</hi> in gold was left behind, being hid under the bench: and forgot to be taken away, this mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney was never miſt untill we came to our Journies end, at night: and it being told my Lord that ſo much money was miſſing, and where they had left it. My Lord made no other words of it, but theſe, <hi>you talk of a cheap reck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oning,</hi>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:116046:18"/> 
                  <hi>but I never paid ſo dearly for a nights lodging in all my life; who would think that a man ſhould leave ſo much money behind him, in ſuch a lowſie Inne:</hi> one that ſtood by told the Marqueſſe, that it was a hundred to one, if ever he heard of his money again, it was ſuch a beggerly houſe. <hi>O peace ſaid the Marqueſs, if they won't be known of the money, you ſhall ſee it will be a brave Inne in time.</hi> This money was ſent after, and very honeſtly reſtored, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered into the Meſſengers hands, that came for it; being brought unto the Marqueſs, there was much wondering at the honeſty of the woman of the houſe: others praiſed the whole Town, for their generall and honeſt dealing, ſeeing it was generally known: the Marqueſſe told them, <hi>That it may be the Town never ſaw ſo much money before, and therefore they knew not what to make on't.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:116046:19"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. 17.</head>
               <p>THe Marqueſſe journying on his way to <hi>Raglan,</hi> happened to come to a place that was called <hi>Strata del florida,</hi> in <hi>Cardiganſhire,</hi> (which made him aske us whither we meant to carry him? ſaying, <hi>That we had brought already to the Weſt Indies,)</hi> an old ruinated, but ſometimes a moſt famous monaſtery; with whoſe ruines was built a pritty tolerable <hi>Welch Gentlemans</hi> houſe, where my Lord lodged that night; in which houſe there was ſhowen unto us, an old, old woman: who was credibly reported, to have been living, and of years able to remember when that Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naſtery was in its flouriſhing condition, and to have been at maſſe often-times when the place was inhabited with <hi>Monks</hi> and <hi>Fryers;</hi> this ſtrange Relation, was no ſooner carried up and preſented to my Lords eares; But my Lord was as greedy to glut his eyes, with ſuch an Object, as they to fill his eares, with the Relation. The woman being ſent for, came,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:116046:19"/> coming, the Marqueſs queſtioned her concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the manner of the <hi>Monks</hi> behaviour, both in their Service, their Orders, Habits, Cuſtomes, and all other particulars; who gave his Lordſhip ſo exact an account, that he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved it to be true, and confeſſed that it muſt needes be ſo; and queſtioning of her further, about her age? ſhe ſaid ſhe was one hundred years of age; then the Marqueſs asked her: And what when the Religion altered, you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered with the Religion? ſhe anſwered no, in truth Maſter, I ſtay'd to ſee, whether or no, the People of the new Religion would be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then the people of the old; and I could ſee them nothing, but grow worſe and worſe, and charity to wax colder and colder, and ſo I kept me to my old Religion, I thank God, and by the grace of God mean to live and die in it: The Marqueſs turned to the Gentleman of the houſe, who was a <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,</hi> and asked him whether or no, ſhe had been noted for a <hi>Papiſt</hi> all her life: the <hi>Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> ſaid that ſhe had, and could never be brought from it, and that ſhe would often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, ſteale into the Church alone with her beades, and there ſhe would be praying by her ſelf; The Marqueſs diſmiſſ'd her for the preſent, but after ſupper, ſent for her again,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:116046:20"/> and had ſome more private conference with her; amongſt other things he asked her, how ſhe did do to ſerve God, and when ſhe had ſeen a Prieſt laſt, when ſhe had been at Maſſe, or received the Sacrament? the woman an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered that ſhe had not ſeen a Prieſt, not in 60. years; but ſhe did ber Office daily, and never miſt, and once a year upon good <hi>Fryday,</hi> ſhe received the Sacrament at the Parſons hands, praying to God, that ſince ſhe could not attain unto the meanes that God would make the Parſon, a Prieſt to her at that day: which ſhe believing God Almighties goodnes to be ſuch, as that he did hear her prayers: the Marqueſs fell into ſuch a fit of laughter, and thence into ſuch expreſſions of admiration, that I never ſaw any man ſo tranſported be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween ſuch extreams, in my life, till at the laſt they both ended in pitty, and commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which wrought in the Marqueſs this ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, and to the poor woman this intended advantage: The Marqueſs gave her 10. peeces of old gold (which ſo gliſtered in the womans eye, that it would have been both a loſſe to her ſelf, and an undervaluation to her Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factor to have taken them for Angels) telling her that if ſhe would go with him to <hi>Raglan,</hi> and ſpend the remainder of her dayes with
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:116046:20"/> him, ſhe ſhould be welcome, and there enjoy the meanes of bringing her thither, where now ſhe had but a little way to go, meaning Heaven, and that ſhe ſhould want for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, neither whilſt he lived nor afterwards, and if there were any friends of hers that were poor, ſhe ſhould give that 10. pounds a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt them, and ſhe ſhould have more: the woman fell a crying, ſaying, over, and over a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, conſtantly, God had ſent him, God had ſent him; he was a good man. And ſo ſhe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted, reſolving to go as ſoone as poſſible, towards <hi>Raglan:</hi> the next news that we could hear in the morning, was, that the poor wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was dead. Whereupon the Marqueſs exceſſively griev'd and wept: all concluding that ſhe dyed with exceſs of joy; whereat the Marqueſs ſaid thus unto us. <hi>If this poor ſoule died for joy, that ſhe ſhould come into a place, where ſhe might ſerve God: how joyfully, will ſhe ſerve him, where ſhe comes into a place, when ſhe ſhall never die.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:116046:21"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. 18.</head>
               <p>ON our way, we were told, that we ſhould come by a place which was famous for miracle, which the tradition of thoſe parts re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, to have been wrought, occaſioned upon St. <hi>Davids</hi> preaching unto 3000. people: who that he might the better be heard: the ground it is ſaid, to riſe up, in a round knob; whereupon St. <hi>David</hi> pitched his Croſſe, whereon he lean'd, whilſt he was preaching; which Croſſe, was yet ſtanding, with ſome words and letters, which time had made unlegible, and that St. <hi>David</hi> had cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed a Church, to be erected in that place, as a memorial of ſo great a miracle; this Relation made the Marqueſs very deſirous, to view the place, the Church and the Croſſe; and ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Church-yard, every man endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring to make ſomething of the obliterated ſuperſcription, and no man could, for there were onely theſe worne peeces of Characters to be ſeen, <hi>viz. Crx. xti. dd.</hi> and a peece of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:116046:21"/> an <hi>S.</hi> which my Lord preſently read it <hi>Crux Chriſti Davidis,</hi> which we all wondering, that no man could find it out, it afterwards ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearing to be ſo plain. He told us, <hi>Look you now, I without my ſpectacles and ill eyes could read it ſooner then all you, that needed none, and had good eyes; it is not a good eye, but a good Faith, that attaines to the knowledge of ſuch things, whilſt you pore ſo much upon the like, you looſe the meaning, now I will tell you, how I came to find it out: I conſidered what had been told me, with the help whereof, I came to underſtand what the words might ſignifie, ſo that in this, I am ſure tradition was a meanes to help me, to the true underſtanding of the Scripture;</hi> leaving the place, as we were going along by the Church-yard Rayle, there was an old woman naked as ever ſhe was borne, who kept her Hermitage between the rootes of an over-grown hallow Tree, ſhe was the moſt lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table ſpectacle of mortality that ever eyes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held; her eyes as hallow as a dead mans ſcull, and her head as bare, nothing but skin and bone, her breſts hanging down like two old lethern pockets, and her belly like a ſatchel, her tawney skin, looking rather as if it had been looſe Garments to the bones; then con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fines to any fleſh and blood; In a word, it
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:116046:22"/> frightned us all, onely the Marqueſs was in love with her, proteſting <hi>That he never ſaw a ſight that did him ſo much good,</hi> ſaying, <hi>how hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py were it for a man that is going to bed to his grave, to be firſt wedded to this Woman.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. 19.</head>
               <p>THe Earl of <hi>Glomorgan,</hi> (the Marqueſs of <hi>Worceſters</hi> eldeſt Sonne) accompanied with divers Officers, Knights, and Gentlemen of high ranck and quality, all of them of the red letter, as they were on their journey for <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> quartered in the Town of <hi>Carnavon</hi> (a Sea Town) in <hi>North-wales,</hi> where they were entertained with diſcourſe at their Table, by ſome of the Gentlemen of the Countrey, which informed them, of the fulfilling of an old <hi>Welch</hi> Prophecy, at that very time and place, which was, <hi>viz,</hi> That there ſhould come a <hi>Mag-pie</hi> and build her neſt in the Crown, then ſhould come a <hi>Jack-daw,</hi> and beat away the <hi>Mag-pie;</hi> and after that, there ſhould come a <hi>Buzzard,</hi> that ſhould beat away
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:116046:22"/> the <hi>Jack-daw;</hi> and then there ſhould be ſeen no Crown but that of thornes, upon the Kings head; at laſt there ſhould come a band of men from a farre Countrey, and take away the thornes, and then the Crown ſhould ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear again: this they ſaid was (thus) hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to accompliſhed. <hi>viz.</hi> over the gate of <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narvon</hi> Caſtle, there was the Picture of King <hi>Edward</hi> 1. in full proportion, with a Crown upon his head; there did come a <hi>Mag-pie,</hi> who did build her neaſt in the ſaid Kings Crown, and a <hi>Jack-daw</hi> did beat away the <hi>Mag-pie,</hi> and the <hi>Buzzard</hi> the <hi>Jack-daw:</hi> this (ſaid the Townſmen) we aſſure your Honour to be true, and all our Townſmen have obſerv'd it; whereupon the Earl of <hi>Glamorgan</hi> replyed, why may not we be that band of men, that ſhall take away theſe thornes, from off the Kings head, firſt in type, and then in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance; we come farre enough off, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, all concluded themſelves to be the men; in order whereunto, they all reſolved, that as ſoone as ever they had fill'd their bellies, they would ſatisfie their eyes, with the ſight, as well as their eares, with the Relation, and lend their helping hands to alter the figure. Dinner being ended, they all went to the Caſtle gate, being come, there they beheld the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:116046:23"/> ſight, the neaſt being diſordered, with the fightings of the Combatants, the materialls made ſuch a mournfull aſpect, as if they had been artificially pleated upon the Kings head, which made Sir <hi>Vinian Moleneus</hi> ſay, that he never beheld a ſadder ſpectacle in all his life. The Earl of <hi>Glamorgan</hi> could not endure the ſight, but ſtreightway Commanded the neaſt to be pull'd down, which was done accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ingly, and being throwen down, they found the materials of the neaſt to be ſuch, as where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with never any bird did build her neaſt, <hi>viz.</hi> with white thorne, which for a memorandum or rarity, every one of them, ſtuck a thorne in his Hat-band, and wore it.</p>
               <p>This ſtory was related to the Marqueſs of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> having heard it, after ſome pawſe, he asked thoſe about him, <hi>what is the nick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>name which the Round-heads uſe to give to the Biſhops?</hi> there were none about him who could gueſſe at his meaning; which he per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving, ſaid, <hi>as I take it, they uſed to call the Biſhops Mag-pies, whom they reproach for build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their neaſts in the Crown; then came the Presbyterian Jack-dawes, and beat them out; and the next thing that you ſhall ſee will be the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendant Buzzards, will drive them away, and who ſhall come next, God knowes.</hi> One with a
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:116046:23"/> 
                  <hi>Roman</hi> noſe, made anſwer. I hope my Lord, that after that theſe men have plaid their prancks ſufficiently; no man will preſume to build his neaſt hereafter in the Crown, but I hope there will be a knot of good fellowes, that may eaſe the Kings head from the prick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of thoſe thornes, and clear the Crown from thoſe incumbrances; whereupon the Marqueſs replying, asked the party that rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted the ſtory, <hi>what manner of Crown it was, that was upon the Kings head?</hi> the Gentleman re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed, a Royal Crown. <hi>I, but I mean ſaid the Marqueſs, was it an open or an imperial Crown?</hi> the Gentleman made anſwer, an open Crown, <hi>O then,</hi> ſaid the Marqueſs, <hi>that was the Reaſon the Kings Crown was too open; had it been cloſe at top, with the Croſſe over head, ſuch unluckie birds could never have come there, to have built their neaſts; but one thing I miſlike in the ſtory, that after they had taken the thornes from the Kings head, they ſhould afterwards weare them in their own Hat-bands.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:116046:24"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. 20.</head>
               <p>I Cannot (well) tell, whether it was, upon the marriage of my Lord <hi>Edward Herbert,</hi> with the Earl <hi>Carnavons</hi> ſiſter, or the Lord <hi>Matague,</hi> with the Marqueſſe of <hi>Worceſters</hi> Daughter; that there happened this merry paſſage, or mock-wedding (as an echo to the voices, that were heard in <hi>Hymeneus</hi> Chappel, between thoſe lovely couple (think which you pleaſe) who had newly left being vvhol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly themſelves, by being half of each other) <hi>viz.</hi> One of thoſe two paire of Lovers, had no ſooner united tvvo hearts in one, and had ſeated themſelves, by one of the too many proprieties belonging unto the honourable ſtate of matrimony, <hi>viz.</hi> the boord, but this <hi>Tom Deputy</hi> an old bachelour, chanc'd to caſt his eye upon a pritty peece of vvaiting vvo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, (one of the appurtenances to this ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable bride) he this jovial <hi>Tom</hi> (having vvhetted his vvit by the ſides of the marriage bovvle) fixes upon (being inabled ſufficiently
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:116046:24"/> thereby to follovv any humour) as a fit ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject to make their Ladiſhips ſome ſport, which happened to be ſo ſutable to the occaſion, and ſo well performed, that it ſoon captivated the eares alſo, of all the maſculine Nobility. (Thus encountring the faire Bride.) Madam, you have the prittieſt peece of neceſſity yonder, at the ſide Table, that I know not how any man can be vvithout her, that may have her for asking, Madam will you give her me? I proteſt I will marry her, and fancy my ſelf to be a Lord, and her ſelf a Lady: My mind to me a Kingdom is, vvhich ſhall make her a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient joynture. <hi>Tom, Tom,</hi> (ſaid the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs) <hi>ſuch men as you and I, whoſe joynts are enfeebled, with the ſtrokes of many years, muſt not think to winne young maides, by promiſing to make them joyntures of the mind; but will you make her Deputy of Deputy-Hall? and Landla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of all the Land that is belonging to it? and Mrs. of all the ſtock that is upon the Land, and Goods that is within the houſe? and then, you ſhall heare what my Daughter, and her woman will ſay unto you.</hi> With all my heart (ſaid <hi>Tom)</hi> and all the Hoggs, and poultry, that is about the houſe to boote: and ſhe ſhall lie upon ſix Feather-beds the firſt night; why then it ſhall be a match (ſaid the Lady) withall my
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:116046:25"/> heart. Give me your hand Madam, (ſayes Deputy) I will have her, if there be no more neceſſary evills in the World, and preſently makes his addreſſes to the pritty little Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>woman of the ſaid Table, who had heard all the diſcourſe, and was perſwaded then up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his approach, to anſwer his humour, with a condeſcention at the firſt word, and inform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that he was an old rich whoreſon: he accoſting her after this manner, this pritty moppit, now thy Lady hath given her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, that I ſhall have thee, if thou ſaiſt ſo too, wee'l be in bed as ſoone as they, with all my heart, and thank you too, ſaid the young Gentlewoman) by my troth a match (ſaid he) give me thy hand, 'tis done: Il'e break ſuch a jeſt (this day) as I never broke in my life; but do not break your promiſe (ſaid the Gentlewoman.) What, before all this Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany (ſaid <hi>Deputy)</hi> that were a ſhame. Up he goes again, to the Lady, and tells her, that they were agreed: my Lady drank to him, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſame condition, he pledged her, and wiſh'd the wine might be his poiſon, if he did not marry her after dinner: The Lady (wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to preferre her vvoman to ſuch a fortune) held him to his vvord, and required perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of his promiſe (giving her many and
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:116046:25"/> high Commendations) <hi>Tom,</hi> went not from any part of his promiſe, onely the time except<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and that in regard he meant to buy him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſome wedding Clothes: the Marqueſs (willing to remove that Obſtacle) told him, that he thought his Clothes would fit him: and bid him goe unto his Wardrope, and take vvhat he had a mind to: give me your key (ſaid <hi>Tom)</hi> it was delivered unto him; up vvent he, and then came down, vvith his Bever Hat, ſattin Cloke, laid with pluſh, dawb'd with a gold &amp; ſilver lace, ſuite of the ſame, ſilk ſtock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, with roſes and Garters ſuitable, inſide &amp; outſide, capape, all as brave, as if he carried a Lordſhip on his back. The Lady Bride takes her vvoman aſide, and dreſſes her in one of her richeſt and new Gownes, (that ſhould have made every day of that week ſenſible of an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change) with all things anſwerable thereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to: not without ſome ſtore of ſlight Jewels, and brings her down, as glorious, as the morne, that breaks from the eaſtern hill, and chaſes night away, they look upon one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and all upon them both. <hi>Tom</hi> cries out, I had beſt be in good earneſt, ſaid my Lady, I thought you had been in ſober ſadnes, neither <hi>(Madam)</hi> ſaid the new Bridegroome and old <hi>Tom,</hi> I hope (ſaid the Lady) you vvill not
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:116046:26"/> make me take all this paines for nothing; no by no meanes (ſaith he) if ever we repent, vve vvill ſell our fine Cloathes, and buy Cattle. It is better being a Lord for a week, then a ſlave for ever. Come thy wayes; happy is the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that is not long a doing: married they were, in the greateſt pomp and Ceremony; and the Queen of beauty, took delight, in looſing the eyes of the vulgar, which by this time, were altogether fixed on the Lady of the May. <hi>Tom</hi> acted his ſcene of mirth in the Hall, which proved to be a thing of that convenience, as if it had been an act of ſome ſet policie, to keep the crowd out of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, that the Maſquers might have roome e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to dance in, at laſt vvhen the Maſque was ended, and time had brought in Supper, the Cuſhine led the dance, out of the parlour, into the Hall, and ſaluted the old-new-made Bridegroome, and his Lady, leading them in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Parlour, to a Table which was furniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, vvith the ſame allowance that vvas alotted for all the Nobles, vvhere they vvere ſoon forced to ſit down firſt. <hi>(Tom</hi> taking upon him as much as they could give him.) In fine, Supper being ended, the Marqueſs of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> asked the Lady Bride, <hi>if ſhe had a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred</hi>
                  <pb n="41" facs="tcp:116046:26"/> 
                  <hi>pounds about her:</hi> ſhe anſwered, no my Lord, but I can ſend for as much, <hi>I pray do,</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſs) <hi>but it muſt be all in gold;</hi> ſhe ſent for it, and preſented it to her Father, who pull'd out another purſe of an hundred peeces, and put the two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred peeces in the Baſon, ſaying, <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, if you do not give earneſt, Deputy will tell you, in the morning, that he married your wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man but in jeſt:</hi> Whereupon, ſome gave fifty, others forty, ſome gave twenty, others ten: the leaſt gave five peeces, who ſate at the Table in all, 700 <hi>l.</hi> The Apparel and other gifts, amounting to no leſſe a value, then one thouſand pounds, vvhich ſo tranſported the old man, that he proteſted, that now he was in the humour, he vvould marry all the wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gentlewomen they had. One every day in the vveek, as long as the vvedding laſted: my Lord <hi>Marqueſs</hi> replyed, <hi>I but Tom, you have left out one thing that you ſhould have ſaid, viz. at this rate.</hi> Not to be too tedious, the man, vvhat vvith bounty, and vvhat with that, vvhich vvas as free to every man, as was their purſes unto him, vvhich vvas good wine, the man was not himſelf, when he ſhould have gone to bed to another, vvhich being related to my Lord, his Lordſhip took an occaſion,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:116046:27"/> to tell the Company, the ſtory of the begger, vvho was made believe, he did but dreame of the happineſs, that was really acted; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon, the Marqueſs was deſirous, to make experiment vvhether it could be related in the perſon of old <hi>Thomas:</hi> in order vvhereunto, he gave Command, that my Friend <hi>Thomas,</hi> ſhould be diſrobed of his next vvedding Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, the reſt of his fine Clothes taken from him, and himſelf carried unto his old Lodging in the Porters Lodge, and his vvife to reſpit the ſolemnization of the Marriage-bed, untill his comportment ſhould deſerve ſo faire an admiſſion: vvhich was done accordingly, the next morning made the experiment to anſwer the height of all their expectations; for news was brought unto the Marqueſs, (all the reſt of the Lords and Ladies ſtanding by) that <hi>Tom</hi> took all yeſterdayes vvork but for a dream, or at leaſt, ſeem'd to do ſo, to humour the fancy. I ſhould be endleſſe, if I ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late unto you, the ſport that this fellow made. To conclude, the <hi>Marqueſs</hi> call'd them both before him, and delivered unto them the money, vvith many good exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions to them both, thus moralizing upon the premiſſes, <hi>viz. That which was firſt in intenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:116046:27"/> 
                  <hi>is oftentimes, both with God, and man, the laſt in execution: as for example, God had be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all Worlds, determined, to ſhew his love to man-kind, by wedding his onely Sonne to his Church; ſo that thus much we have gain'd al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready,</hi> viz. <hi>That the Marriage, that was made in Paradiſe, between</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Eve, <hi>though it was the firſt in time, yet it was but ſecondary, to the firſt intention; and he that ſaid, before</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham <hi>was,</hi> I am: <hi>was alſo, before</hi> Adam <hi>was, and though the firſt Marriage, was but a type of the ſecond, yet the ſecond, (according to the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid intention) was an antecedent to the firſt. God, who having an intention, to wed his Sonne to his beloved ſpouſe, the Church: gave way to this type or figure, or (to bring the ſimilitude a little homer) mock-wedding, which was between</hi> Adam <hi>and</hi> Eve, <hi>whom to make appear more wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy and glorious, in the eyes of his beloved, and all other Creatures, he array'd with full Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and the Robe of righteouſneſs his mercy (the Lady and Empreſs of all the glorious at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes of God) arrai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> this type and figure of his Church, with the Robe of innocence, and gives thom both a large proportion of his grace. Theſe bleſſings,</hi> Adam <hi>(by taſting the forbidden fruit) loſt his Paradiſe and ſlept in death.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:116046:28"/>
               <p> Gentlemen. <hi>I will not make any appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation hereof, leaſt I may ſeeme to miſtruſt your wiſdomes, but I have nothing to ſay to the Woman.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:116046:28"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. 21.</head>
               <p>THe Marqueſs of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> calling for a Glaſſe of <hi>Claret-wine,</hi> it was told him by his <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> that <hi>Claret-wine</hi> was nought for his Gout: <hi>What my old Friend, Claret, nay give it me</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſs) <hi>in ſpight of all Phyſitians and their Bookes, it never ſhall be ſaid, that I forſooke my Friend for mine E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:116046:29"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. 22.</head>
               <p>DUring the time of the ſiege of <hi>Raglan,</hi> there came a Musket Bullet in at the vvindow of the with-drawing roome (where my Lord was uſed to entertain his Friends, with his pleaſant diſcourſes after dinners and ſuppers) which glancing upon a little marble piller of the vvindow, and from thence, hit the Marqueſs upon the ſide of his head; and fell down flatted upon the Table, which breaking the piller in peeces, it made ſuch a noiſe in the roome, that the Counteſſe of <hi>Gla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morgan</hi> (who ſtood in the ſame vvindow) ran away, as if the houſe had been falling down upon her head: crying out, O Lord, O Lord, but finding her ſelf more afraid then hurt: ſhe returned back again, no leſſe excuſing her (as ſhe was pleaſed to call it) rudeneſſe to her Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; then acknowledging her fears to all the Company: to whom the Marqueſs ſaid, <hi>Daughter, you had reaſon to run away, when</hi>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:116046:29"/> 
                  <hi>your Father was knockt on the head:</hi> and paw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing ſome while, and turning the flatted bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let round with his finger, he further ſaid, <hi>Gentlemen. Thoſe who had a mind to flatter me, were wont to tell me, that I had a good Head<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peece in my younger dayes; but if I do not flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter my ſelf, I think I have a good Head-peece, in my old age, or elſe it would not have been Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket-proofe.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:116046:30"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. 23.</head>
               <p>ONe was telling the Marqueſs, how ſtrangely I eſcaped a ſhot, by the Barre of a vvindow (looking out into the Leager) as thus: ſtanding in a vvindow of the Caſtle, there came a Musket-bullet, and hit full againſt the edge of an Iron Barre of a Chamber vvindow, ſo that it parted the bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let in two, the barre expatiating it ſelf (by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees) towards the middle; one half of the bullet flew by me, on the one ſide, and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther half on the other ſide, ſo that (by Gods providence) I had no hurt: the Marqueſſe hearing this, asked me, <hi>in what Chamber it was,</hi> I told him, his Lordſhip ſaid, <hi>as I remember, the window was croſſe bard, and you will never believe me, how ſafe it is, to ſtand before the Croſſe, when you face your Enemy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:116046:30"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. 24.</head>
               <p>THe Marqueſſe of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> was alwayes wont (towards his la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter times) to dine and ſup, by himſelf, and being asked the Reaſon (by one who thought he might be ſo bold) and told that it would be more de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lightfull, and chearfull to him, then to dine and ſup by himſelf; he made an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>That he knew not what delight a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny man could take, to ſhew himſelf mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall.</hi> The Inquiſitor made anſwer, that every man did know, and believe that he did eat, and therefore he did not appear leſſe mortall, by appearing
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:116046:31"/> ſo mortall: My LORD reply'd, <hi>Every man knowes and believes, that I empty, as well as fill, my body: yet it is not neceſſary, that I expreſſe that mortality, but rather ſeek out pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacie:</hi> The party that broach'd the Diſcourſe, further ſaid: My LORD, it is the maine occaſion of humane ſociety, and if humane ſociety were debarr'd of that occaſion of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placence; mirth would have no roome to dance, according to the old Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbe, <hi>'tis merry in Hall, when beards wagge all.</hi> O (ſaid the MARQUESSE,) SOLOMON <hi>was a wiſe man, but he appropriated muſick to a Banquet of wine: and not to a Table fill'd with the mangled fleſh, and Carkeſſes of ſo many ſlaine Creatures: that ſhould ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther put us in mind of our own mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tality, and ſinnes, (ſeeing our lives are neceſſitated thereby, to be repaired by the death of ſo many Martyrs) and</hi>
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:116046:31"/> 
                  <hi>the Heathens ſuppoſed, their Gods to drink wine, but never to eate any meate.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:116046:32"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. 25.</head>
               <p>THere was a great man in the <hi>KINGS</hi> Army, between whom and the houſe of <hi>Raglan,</hi> there was (at that time) animoſity. The Marqueſſe of WGRCESTER had heard, that this party ſhould caſt a dubious ſaying, (as the caſe then ſtood) <hi>viz. That he, intended to take</hi> RAGLAN <hi>in his way,</hi> and was ſo farre as good as his word as that he marcht into the Parke, and there drew up his men, and fac'd the Caſtle; whereupon, the line was man'd and Command was given, that none ſhould be ſuffered to come near the line (within ſuch a diſtance) which Command was ſo obſerv'd, that ſome
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:116046:32"/> of the Officers of the Army (approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within the place prohibited) the Centry bid ſtand: they did not, the Centry call'd upon them again, to ſtand: they refuſed, the Lieutenant call'd upon the Centry to give fire: the Centry (preferring the knowledge of his Friends before his Duty to his Officer, did not give fire; but ſwore, he would give fire if they did not ſtand: whereupon, one of them told him, that it was ſuch a Generall, and wonder'd, that the Officer would bid the Souldier give fire upon him: the Generall forthwith, coming to the Draw-bridge, deſir'd to ſpeak with the Lord <hi>CHARLES:</hi> whom he no ſooner ſaluted, but required ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction for the affront; he was deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to come into the Caſtle, and told that the matter ſhould be examined before him, and if any affront were given, he ſhould receive ſatisfaction: whereupon, being come within the
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:116046:33"/> Caſtle, the Lieutenant was ſent for, who told the General, that though he knew him to be the General, yet (as a Souldier,) he was not to take any no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of him, untill ſuch time as he had declar'd himſelf, which when he did, he reſpected him accordingly: fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thermore, telling him, that he had been an old Souldier, and that he had in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts, ſeen rewards given unto Souldiers (who ſtood Centry) for firing upon their Generall, having the like occaſions, but never knew it a fault before. All this would not ſerve turn, the Generall ſaid he was affronted, and muſt have ſatisfaction, requiring my <hi>LORD</hi> to call a Councell of Warre, and to do him juſtice, and ſo took his leave, and went his way. The Marqueſs of <hi>WORCESTER</hi> ſleep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon his bed all this while, and not dreaming of any of all this that had happened in the interim, hearing the whole Relation, he asked all his
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:116046:33"/> Officers, <hi>whether or no the Lieutenant had offended?</hi> they all anſwered no, and commended him, for what he had done: then ſaid the Marqueſſe, <hi>This is but a pretence, they have a mind to quarrel with us: If ye ſhould call a Councell of Warre, and acquit him: that is it that they deſire, and thence they would ground their quarrel, and if ye ſhould inflict any puniſhment upon him, to give them ſatisfaction, that were baſeneſſe and injuſtice: therefore I will have it thus, ſend a Guard with him, to the Generall, of ſuch Souldiers as are able to witneſſe the truth, and let him try him at his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of Warre, and ſee what Law he hath for it, and ſo we ſhall break the neck of the quarrell:</hi> and ſo ſaid the Lieutenant, I ſhall hang by the neck for my labour: whereat the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe replyed, <hi>What friends haſt thou in the Gariſon?</hi> The Lieutenant made anſwer, I have a Wife and a
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:116046:34"/> Daughter; then ſaid the Marqueſs with ſome vehemence, <hi>I proteſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, if they hang thee, Il'e mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thy wiſe, and provide for thy Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:</hi> The Lieutenant reply'd, I had rather you would marry my Daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, and provide for me. <hi>I proteſt,</hi> ſaid the Marqueſſe, <hi>ſo I will, I will marry thy Daughter, and I will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide for thee—an honourable grave, but you ſhall be hang'd firſt.</hi> My Lord, ſaid the Lieutenant, ſhall I beſpeake my grave? <hi>Thou ſhalt,</hi> ſaid the Marqueſſe, then ſaid the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renant, I will be laid in the vault in <hi>Raglan</hi> Church, between your Father, and your Grandfather, and I pray God I may be hang'd before I ſee you again: and ſo flung out of the roome, leaving my LORD in the merrieſt vaine, that ever I ſaw him: who remembring himſelf, ſent him five peeces to beare his Charges. The Lieutenant
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:116046:34"/> being brought to the Generall, to <hi>Monmouth:</hi> The Generall diſmiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him of his Guard, and ſent him to <hi>Hereford,</hi> with an Oath at his heeles. that he would hang him, if there were no more men in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Then the Lieutenant cry'd out, this makes for us, I do but think how finely, I ſhall lie between the two old EARLES; and how fine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the old EARLE will lie between my Daughters two young leggs. The particulars hereof, being brought to the Marqueſſe, the Marqueſſe was not a little perplext, between feare of having his new Miſtreſſe, and looſing his old Friend: which he had runne himſelf into, between jeſt, and earneſt: The time was come, that the Marqueſſe was not ſo much merrier then we, hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore; but we were as much merrie as he, upon the return of this
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:116046:35"/> newes. But the greateſt ſport of all, was, concerning the hopefull Lady Marqueſſe, who was ever and anon, inquiring and asking many queſtions, concerning the Marqueſſe, whom ſhe never ſaw) what manner of man he was? how old? whether he went with a ſtaffe or no? what was the reaſon he kept his Chamber ſo much, and did not come abroad ſome times? what Diſeaſes he had? and how long agoe it was ſince his Lady dyed? with many other neceſſary queſtions to be asked, by a woman in her con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition: ſport enough there was for both the Gariſons, <hi>Raglan</hi> and <hi>Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford:</hi> nevertheleſſe, it ſtood the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe upon, to be ſollicitous in the buſineſſe, being ſore preſt, between two ſtrong paſſions, love and pitty, Me he ſends to ſollicit the buſineſſe, with inſtructions; whoſe telling me (never ſo often) <hi>that it was no laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing matter,</hi> could not make me for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bear
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:116046:35"/> laughing. But having taken my leave, his Lordſhip call'd me back a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, and with a loud and angry voice ſaid to me, <hi>tell the Generall, that if he hang my Lieutenant, I'le hang the Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, for not giving fire upon him when he was bid:</hi> whereupon I ſaid unto his Lordſhip, what doth he care how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny you hang? <hi>God bleſſe us all</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſſe) <hi>if he neither cares who he hangs, [of the Kings party] nor who o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther folkes hang, for ought I know, he cares not, and they were all hang'd.</hi> So taking my ſecond leave of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs, and then my humble leave of the Lady <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who fearing nothing more but that I would prove too good a Sollicitour for her good, I went to <hi>Hereford,</hi> and made ſome ſport there, and ſo brought home the Lieutenant to his Wife and Daughter, who ever after was called my Lady Marqueſs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:116046:36"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. 26.</head>
               <p>THe Marqueſſe would often ſay, <hi>That all the inconveniencies, that the frailty of humane nature, was inci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent to fall into, ever happened, through the want of this conſideration, had, at the end of every action, before ever we enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prized, a beginning, viz.</hi> What then.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:116046:36"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. 27.</head>
               <p>HE was wont to ſay, <hi>That a plain dealing Friend, whoſe friendly Councel, was requited with choller, and diſguſt, was like a turfe, that (whilſt a man beſtowed breath upon it to inliven it) returnes thanks to the well-willer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by ſpitting fire in his face.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:116046:37"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. 28.</head>
               <p>WE were talking of an old drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken fellow, who (having us'd his body to diſorder, in drinking all his life time, and at laſt giving it over) preſently dyed. <hi>O</hi> [ſaid the Marqueſs] <hi>if you take a brand out of the fire, that is thoroughly burnt, it will fall in peeces; but if you let it lie there ſtill, it may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine a pritty while, before it turne to aſhes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:116046:37"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. 29.</head>
               <p>THe Marqueſs was a very devout man, and us'd prayer very much, and you ſhould never ſee his cloſet doore open, but you might perceive he had been weeping, which he would en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour to conceale, by wiping his eyes; but he could never wipe away either the ſwelling, or the redneſs [as it was commonly obſerv'd by all the Servants, that had neareſt relation to him, and indeed to all thoſe, who had any familiarity with him] for after dinner, he admitted all Gentlemen in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to his preſence, whom he would con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly entertain with a Chapter ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther out of the book of patience, or elſe out of <hi>Derxelius</hi> upon eternity, or out of an excellent Manuſcript called,
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:116046:38"/> 
                  <hi>The love of God,</hi> which had 100. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters all upon that Subject, which he would read with ſuch devotion, that often-times his teares would over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw their bankes, which I having obſerv'd to be ſo frequently perform'd told him, I thought it did him much hurt. No [ſaid the Marqueſs] <hi>This iſſue of the ſoule muſt not be ſtopt, if you knew but what a fire I have to quench, you would rather wiſh me to provide more water. Have you not ſuch a ſaying in Scripture, that they who ſowe in teares ſhall reap in joy? I wiſh that I could ſo weepe, all my life, that I might laugh in death, and ſing in Heaven, and I were a happy man.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:116046:38"/>
               <head>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>OPHTH. XXX.</head>
               <p>I Was walking one day with his Lordſhip in a private walk that was about the round Tower: and there we ſpied where a bird had made her neſt, whom we di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb'd from hatching her young ones and ſitting upon her eggs: which act of nature my Lord compared unto the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the creation; for ſaid he, God ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving made his neſt the world, and brought forth his young <hi>at firſt unperfected, did by his ſpirit</hi> incubare <hi>and by his wings of providence ſpread over them he gave them life and power, and by his word he brake the ſhel,</hi> et ſic pullu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lavit mundum.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. XXXI.</head>
               <p>WE were talking upon occaſion of Chriſts miracles; <hi>viz</hi> of his turning water into wine, and of the five loaves and two fiſhes, why (ſaid the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe)</hi> theſe miracles he works amongſt us every day; but that <hi>they are ſo ordinary un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to us that we take no notice of them: God ſends rain upon the earth: this water gets up into the vine: and the ſappe of the vine-tree,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:116046:39"/> God turneth into wine. And as few graines of Corne, as will make five louves (being ſowed in the earth) will multiply, and increaſe to ſuch advantage as will feed 5000 with bread; and two fiſhes will bring forth ſo many fiſhes, as will ſuffice ſo many mouthes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. XXXII.</head>
               <p>WE were diſcourſing before him, concerning the errour of the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nichees, who held that there were two cauſes of heaven and earth, <hi>viz.</hi> that the good and white God, made the heaven and man, from the middle upward: and the black and evill God, was the effici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent cauſe of the earth, and of man, from the middle downward. That was but a fooliſh Conceit (ſaid the Marqueſs:) <hi>ſo Gods power and wiſdom is ſhown and ſeen, as well in an Ant, as in an Elephant: as well in a worm as in an angell: ſo his Godhead and might appears, as well in the earth, as in the heavens: but methinks it had been (on my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit) a pretty fancie, and not ſo far from truth or reaſon, if they had held, that heaven and earth had been man and wife, or male and female: ſeeing the heaven was made as the male part of the world, by whoſe influence,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:116046:39"/> motion and dewes the earth as the female part thereof (out of her wombe) brings forth all ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary and living Creatures.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. XXXIII.</head>
               <p>THe Marqueſs, was of a diſpoſition, allways inclining to charitable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions: which ſuffered him to want excuſes or ſome cloake or other to throw over any mans imperfection. There was a Gentleman of high deſert, who chanced in the Marqueſſes hearing to come under the laſh of ſome mens Cenſures: <hi>Alas Gentleman</hi> ſaid the Marques, <hi>will you have Corne to grow without chaffe?</hi> or light <hi>to be without its adjoyning darkeneſſe? or the ſweeteſt hony without unſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vory wax? or the pleaſant wines or liquors, without their lees and dreggs? as ſoon ſhall corn grow without chaffe, as a man of his parts ſhall be free from vain glory: worthleſſe chaffe keeps the corn warme, and vain glory fires him to all thoſe brave atchievements: if you ſet a man on an horſe let him have his ſpurrs.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="34" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:116046:40"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. XXXIV.</head>
               <p>THe Marques was one day reading us a Lecture of patience in our adverſity: among the reſt of thoſe witty ſayings which came from him, he told us, that <hi>there was nothing ſo bad but was good for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, for</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>if there were no ſilence, there would be no muſick; for the ſuddain ſtops that are in muſick, adde to the grace and perfection of the Art: ignorance, is a ſpur to knowledge: darkneſs, a pavilion to the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty: a Cabbin or drawn Chamber, for us to ſleep in a Dungeon for the Judge to puniſh his Delinquents, and a foile for the Painter to make his ſhadowes: ſo are afflictions, good for our inſtructions; and adverſities for our a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendments.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. XXXV.</head>
               <p>THere was an old rich <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſurer</hi> and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicator: who had a plot upon the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and eſtate, of a handſome young Widow &amp; an inheritrix of an Eſtate, which this old miſer thought, rather convenient, then great enough for him: wherefore having a mind, rather to enjoy, then have her: and knowing that ſhe was in
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:116046:40"/> debt, courted her with offering to leave her monies, as an argument of his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, which ſhe accepted of, offering to bind her Eſtate for the repayment: ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping that the tie of his perſon, would be a freedom of her Eſtate: thus with his mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, he got his foot into her Eſtate, and by a falſe promiſe ſtept into her bed as of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten as he had a mind to lie doubly, ſix yeares he ſtav'd her off, who bedſtav'd him in, within her own ſleeping-room: but at laſt, that ſhe might be ſure of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance: ſhe urg'd him to the ceremony, and that ſo much, that at laſt he gave her a flat deniall; whereupon ſhe denies him the former familiarity: he enters upon her Eſtate, and anſwers the kindneſs of her admittance of him into her own bed, with the diſcourſe, of turning her out of her own doores: ſhe makes the Marques her friend, declaring unto him how much ſhe had been abus'd by him: and withall, that ſhe was willing to pay him his money, but not the uſe of it, as he required: who thereby thought that he had ſtruck her deep enough, for ever obtaining a recove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry: the Marqueſs ſent for this whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and offer'd himſelf a mediator: the man was unwilling to that; yet knew
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:116046:41"/> not (well) how to deny him: which the Marqueſs perceiving, called him aſide, and bid him get her to be bound with him in a bond of 500 pound, to ſtand to ſuch an a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward as he ſhould make between them: promiſing him faithfully, that he would award him uſe upon uſe. O my Lord: if you do ſo, I ſhall be much oblig'd to your honour, and will be bound with all my heart: and will ſend you a couple of the braveſt colts, and of your Lordſhips own breed, as any is in the Country: well, well, ſaid the Marqueſs, let it be ſo then. All was done accordingly; and when the buſineſs was examined, and found to be as was before related, the Marqueſs made this award, <hi>viz. Sir,</hi> ſaid he to the man, <hi>ſhe hath had the uſe of your money ſo long, and you have had the uſe of her body ſo long: and there is uſe upon uſe; ſo I have allowed you what I promiſed;</hi> whereupon the poor man, lookt, as if he would have ſunk down dead in the place; which the Marqueſs perceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, asked, <hi>why would you have both your prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipall and your intereſt?</hi> And reaſon good my <hi>Lord,</hi> ſaid the fellow, <hi>why then, you ſhal have both,</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſs) <hi>here take her; for if you will not take both in her, you ſhall take neither without her; for I award you, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:116046:41"/> 
                  <hi>to marry her forthwith, or elſe to looſe both your principall and intereſt: could you have ſo little conſcience, as to take ſo much conſideration for the uſe of a little pie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e, and allow no conſideration, both for the uſe and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe of ſuch a creature as this, whoſe prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment you have marr'd: whoſe credit you have taken away: and whoſe fortunes you (thus) go about to deprive her, and her children of? can you think a bond made before a</hi> Scrivener, <hi>and ſigned by ſuch Witneſſes, ſuch a ſtrong tie on your part? and do you think that ſuch an obligation made to her, before ſuch a publick not ary as God Almighty: and witneſſed by men and Angels, ſhould be no tie on her be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half? go, go, take her to you, and marry her, and let me hear no more of it; for if I do, you ſhall ſoone hear from me.</hi> The man being by this time ſchool'd into ſome conformity, proteſted unto the Marqueſs, that if ſhe had prov'd with child, he would have mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried her. <hi>O</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſs) <hi>if that be all, Ile run a hazard, if ſhe brings you no children: you ſhall pay me my two colts, but at the day of the birth of your firſt child.</hi> And thereupon he diſmiſs'd them who were ſoone after married.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:116046:42"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. XXXVI.</head>
               <p>IT was ordinary with the Marqueſs, to entertain diſcourſe with every man, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the condition and profeſſion he was of: And moſt commonly from the beginning of his diſcourſe, you ſhould ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver know what the end would be; Taking delight to deceive the expectation of his auditor. Upon a time there was preſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto him a Lawyer, and he was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form'd before hand, how excellent a man he was in his profeſſion. The Marqueſs thought with himſelf, how he might poſe him, and being brought in with other Gentlemen. After they had dined, he was preſented unto the Marqueſs: <hi>Sir,</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſs,) <hi>I have received a very good Character of you: they ſay, you are very learned in the Law: I would very fain aske you one queſtion,</hi> any thing my Lord, ſaid the Lawyer, that lies within my poor ability. <hi>I pray</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſs,) <hi>who was the firſt man that ever had a</hi> Dedimus pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtatem <hi>granted unto him?</hi> The Lawyer was ſo confounded, that he knew not what to ſay, for a long time: at laſt he made a long and learned diſcourſe, concerning the ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginall
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:116046:42"/> of that writ. And the Marqueſs gave him the hearing, but when he had done, He told him, <hi>that he came far ſhort of the Origin thereof. For Adam was the firſt that ever had</hi> plenitudinem poteſtatis <hi>granted unto him, viz. when God gave him power to ſubdue the earth, and to have Dominion over every li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving creature,</hi> the Lawyer thankt his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and told him, that he thought the Law, had not been ſo antient. <hi>Antient</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſs) <hi>there was the beginning of all your Courts of Juſtice. But I ſee you are but a common Lawyer that cannot derive your pedegree from thence.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. XXXVII.</head>
               <p>THere was a new married couple, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented before the Marqueſs: the Bride a goodly, proper woman, her face well featur'd, an excellent eye ſhe had; but was pittifull diſ-figured with the ſmall pox: the Marqueſs looking much upon her, and ſaying nothing to her a long while: we all know that ſilence was in labour for ſome notable production. At laſt, he advances toward the young Bride, and asked her, <hi>Gentlewoman, do you know, why it is ſaid that God Almighty created man, and builded wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man?</hi> the Gentlewoman ſomewhat out
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:116046:43"/> of countenance anſwered, no indeed my Lord: the Marqueſs asked her again, <hi>do you know why you (women) are called houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wives?</hi> I think my Lord, ſaid the Bride, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe good wives ſhould keep at home, and not gad abroad. <hi>It is a good anſwer</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſs) <hi>but not the right: for women may be bad wives at home as wel as abroad: or elſe they would never ſcold their husbands out of doores. The anſwer to my firſt queſtion is: wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is not ſaid to be made, as</hi> Adam <hi>was, which onely ſignifies plain work; but to be built, which ſignifies curioſity, &amp; contrivance: and therefore as to my ſecond queſtion; a wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is called a houſewife, becauſe ſhe is a houſe, out of which all the Royal Families of Kings and Emperors, derive their extract; nether are you onely compared unto houſes, but unto Cities Kingdoms, Churches and Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealths: but do you know what houſe you are like?</hi> no indeed my Lord, ſaid the Bride, <hi>why then Ile tell you, when God builded the firſt woman, he made her his Store-houſe, wherein he had laid up all the race of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, wherewith he repleniſhed the whole earth; but I muſt tell you Lady, God Almigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty did not make you Coaches nor Waggons, that you ſhould be alwayes gadding abroad:</hi> whereat the Bridegroom made anſwer, my Lord, I thank you for this, I hope my wife
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:116046:43"/> will remember it; my Lord, ſaid the young Bride, you will read ſuch a lecture to my husband, that he will never let me go a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad; <hi>O Lady</hi> (ſaid the Marq.) <hi>he muſt not debar you of that liberty, provided that you ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver go abroad but when you go out like the ſnaile, who ſeldom ſtirs abroad, but whilſt that bleſſing (the dew of heaven) is upon her earth, that ſhe may gather benefit, and by her great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt care, and equal management ſtill carries her houſe upon her back:</hi> O my Lord (ſaid ſhe) If I ſhould go abroad like the ſnaile, I ſhould carry a houſe upon my back, and hornes in my forehead; <hi>No Lady,</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſs) <hi>though ſhe forkes at you, yet they are no hornes: the ſnaile can ſoon draw them in if you touch them, which no horned crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture can perform; but ſhe carries them in her head, to teach you what you ſhould provide, and bear in your mind, againſt you go to hay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>making:</hi> but the Marqueſs fearing that he had a little diſpleaſed her, he thought to make her amends by this following diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe. <hi>Sir,</hi> (ſaid he, to the new Bride<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groom) <hi>you know I have compared your wife unto a building, and I muſt commend your choice; for</hi> (ſaid he, alluding unto her dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fugurement) <hi>a goodly houſe, muſt not be cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen by the ſmoothneſs or whiteneſs of the wall: for ſuch a one, may be but a dairy-houſe, or a
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:116046:44"/> milk-houſe: nor according to the colours or paintings of the out-ſide, for ſuch a one may be but a Tavern or an Ale-houſe: but if I ſee a houſe that is lofty, and ſtately built, and have faire windowes, though the outſide be but ruffcaſt, yet I am ſure, there are goodly roomes within.</hi> And ſo both parties were well pleas'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. XXXVIII.</head>
               <p>IT was told the Marqueſs, that ſuch a Romane Catholike being ſorely preſſed to take the oath of ſupremacy, and being acquainted with another Gentleman, who was a Proteſtant, and ſo like unto him, that you could hardly diſtinguiſh them, whilſt they were together, much leſſe aſunder: this <hi>Imago ſui,</hi> as if nature had choſen him to be his repreſentative, as the others part, (the right ſtone being pulled out, and a Counterfeit ſet in the right ring) and what with the likeneſs of his countenance, and the identity of apparel, he paſt for cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, which jeſt my Romane thought ſo good, that he muſt needes brag of it to the Marqueſs; but the Marqueſs no way
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:116046:44"/> lik'd it, asking him, <hi>would you put another upon that which you would not do your ſelf? what if the Devil (you two being ſo like one another) ſhould miſtake you for him? I aſſure you he would go neere to marre the conceit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. XXXIX.</head>
               <p>THe Marqueſs had an old Servant, one <hi>Redman;</hi> this man was ſo much his Lordſhips, that in all his lifetime (which for the moſt part was ſpent in his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips ſervice) he was never heard to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradict his Lord in his opinion; but to eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry thing that his Lord ſhould ſay, (right or wrong) he ſtill would anſwer his Lord, <hi>I an't like your Lordſhip.</hi> It hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened that upon a time when the Marques was much divided within himſelf, and rackt by Councel, that this <hi>Redman</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the Room, the Marqueſs chanced to ask <hi>Redman</hi> his opinion, (declaring his own) old <hi>Redman</hi> conſtant to his old re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, anſwered his Lordſhip according to his old wont; <hi>I an't like your Lordſhip;</hi> whereupon one that was by, who at that time was contrary to the Marques in his o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinion,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:116046:45"/> &amp; not a little angry with this <hi>Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans</hi> cukcow play, was thus bold with his Lordſhip, my Lord you have a man here, that I dare ſay, ſhould your Lordſhip ſay unto him, wel <hi>Redman,</hi> thou knoweſt how I have ſerved God all my life, and now thou ſeeſt how he deales with me at laſt, in delivering me up into mine enemies hands: introth now <hi>Redman,</hi> we'le even change Maſters, and ſerve the Devil, and ſee what good that will do us; and if <hi>Redman</hi> do not anſwer you, <hi>I an't like your Lordſhip</hi> I durſt be hanged; whereat the Marqueſs reply'd no no, I do not think ſo: wouldſt thou <hi>Redman? Redman</hi> either not hearing well what had been ſaid, or elſe, more to follow his own Vote, then to take off Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections, anſwered, <hi>ant' like your Lordſhip, I would even take that courſe, and let them all ſay what they would.</hi> The next day after the Caſtle was to be ſurrendred, and the Marqueſs had Commanded, that word ſhould be brought him, when the General was entred the Caſtle, that he might meet him in the Hall, the Generall being entred the outward gate, this <hi>Redman</hi> came unto his Lord, and told him, <hi>An't like your Lordſhip,</hi> Sir Thomas <hi>is entred the Caſtle.</hi> The Marqueſſe being diſpoſed to
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:116046:45"/> expreſſe an undauntedneſs in that revoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of affaires, did in this merriment of beha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour at that very inſtant reply. <hi>Redman</hi> (ſaith he, as he was going to meet the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall) <hi>this is the end of all flatterers, to flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter us whilſt we are in proſteritie, and then to jeer us as ſoone as ever we come into adverſity.</hi> I proteſt my Lord, I ſpeak, ſaid <hi>Redman,</hi> really; he is comming. <hi>O Redman</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſs) if thou ſpeakeſt really, thou wouldſt never make <hi>a queſtion, whether it like me or no.</hi> Redman reply'd with a greater vehemence then before, I proteſt before God, an't like your Lordſhip, it is true. <hi>Looke you,</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſs) <hi>Sir Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas is no ſooner entred the caſtle but he is turned proteſtant,</hi> and by this we could ſee through the window, the General with all his officers entring the outward Court, as if a flood-gate had been let open: which the Marqueſs perceiving asked Redman, <hi>how be thought that that could like him,</hi> and leaning towards me, whom he (then) leand upon as the Genenerall was advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing towards him, he ſaid theſe words in my ear, let theſe men ſay what they will; and do <hi>what they can, we ſhall never be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>done till we be damn'd: which was a ſaying</hi> which he often <hi>uſed when he</hi> heard of any mans undoing.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:116046:46"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. XL.</head>
               <p>There was a very ingenious man, and a good artiſt, one <hi>Duckworth</hi> the Queens ſervant and Cabinet-maker this man fall<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing low under the Common calamity, I found in Oxford ſomewhat impoveriſhed, whom I brought along with me to Rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan; ſuppoſing there might be ſome uſe made of him: he was no ſooner there, but beholding the Cutting down of certain trees, which ſtood neer unto the Gariſon, &amp; might be a ſhelter to the beſiegers ſtanding by ſome woodmen, who were ſelling down a maple-tree, the hatchet of one of the fellers chanc'd to ſtrike out a chip of the excreſcency thereof; which being natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally curld and ſingularly various both in ſhape and coulours, this <hi>Duckworth</hi> takes it up in his hand, ſaying, I will make my Lord Marqueſſe the fineſt Tobacco-box that ever he had in his life, and ſo did, and preſented it unto his Lordſhip. The Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs knew not whether it was wood or marble, nor any man elſe, nor what it was made of; all admire it; at laſt being told the particulars, the Marqueſſe when he had admir'd it ſufficiently, gave him a
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:116046:46"/> piece, <hi>Duckworth</hi> told him that it was too much in regard that his Lordſhip found the Materials; what a grateful man is this (ſaid the Marqueſs) <hi>to acknowledge a bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit which would have been nothing worth without his labour?</hi> and thereupon he began (as his cuſtome was, to apply every thing to ſome divine and heavenly meditation) <hi>God Almighty gives every man a ſtock or meaſure of grace, which he muſt poliſh and improve by his own endeavours, for (Sir) had you brought me my chip as you found it, I would not have given you thanks.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. XLI.</head>
               <p>NEver was there a noble houſe ſo pul'd down by Propheſies, uſher'd into its ruin by predictions, and ſo lay'd hold upon by ſignes and tokens; I ſhall tell you no more but what I have both read and ſeen long before the fall of that proud fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brick, which had the honour to fall the laſt of any that ſtood upon the tearmes of honour. There was an old book of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſies which was preſented to the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs, becauſe it ſo much concerned <hi>Rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan</hi> Caſtle. Wherein there were theſe pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, <hi>viz.</hi> That there ſhould come an
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:116046:47"/> Earl that ſhould firſt build a white gate before the Caſtle-houſe, and after that ſhould begin to build a red one, but before that red one ſhould be finiſhed, there ſhould be Wars over all the Land, this was fulfill'd in the Marqueſſes time, who having built the one, and begun the other by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the diſtractions of the time, left the later work unfiniſhed; ſome ſtanding re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſted his Lordſhip to make haſte to fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his red Gate-houſe, becauſe we ſhould have no quiet untill that were up. Hark ye ſaid the Marqueſs, none ſhall prophecie ſo much money out of my purſe in ſuch times as theſe, beſides the prophet doth not ſay until, but before, and for ought I know, if I ſhould make haſte with that building, I ſhould haſten the War to my own door; for the Prophet ſayes, that before the red Gate-houſe ſhall be finiſhed, there ſhall be Wars over all the Land; but what if I had built neither the one nor the other, how would this Propheſie have concern'd me? O my Lord, ſaid one, it is done, and you could not otherwiſe chuſe but do what you did, <hi>I but</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſs) <hi>I can chuſe whether I wil believe the Prophet.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another Prophecie there was, that the King ſhould loſe a great battle, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:116046:47"/> fly to <hi>Raglan,</hi> the enemy ſhould pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue him, and then ſhould leave the Caſtle, and that then the Enemy ſhould beſiedge and put fire to the Caſtle-wall, which was fulfilled, for they burnt the Caſtle: Alſo of an <hi>Eagle</hi> that ſhould come into the Park, and be there ſlain, which ſhould be a fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>runner to the deſtruction of that houſe. Which I ſaw literally perform'd, but ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecuted by one who heard not of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie: Alſo of a Cloud of <hi>Bats</hi> that ſhould hang over the Caſtle a little before its demoliſhment, this three dayes before, all the Caſtle beheld to their no ſmall a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtoniſhment. Which continued about a quarter of an hour, about twilight, ſo thick, that you could not towards the middle of them, ſee the skie, though clear, which being ſhot at with haile-ſhot, ſome of them fell down, and the reſt fled away: the Marqueſs being told of this, he asked what thoſe kind of Creatures might ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie? ſome about him told him, that they were emblems of ruin and deſolation. He asked if they were all gone? it was told him that they were; whereupon the Marqueſs asked us whether or no the Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my had begirt us round? it was anſwered, that they had: then ſaid the Marques; I am
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:116046:48"/> glad of it; for then theſe emblems of ruin cannot fly a way from us, but they muſt fly over ſome of their heads.</p>
               <p>But the ſtrangeſt Propheſie of all, if you will pardon the digreſſion, both for ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication and accompliſhment, is this which I ſhal ſet down unto you in <hi>terminis,</hi> which I read before I ſaw it in this book 14. years before the War, craving pardon of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Reader, for troubling him with ſo much <hi>Welch,</hi> whilſt I intend a ſerene to thoſe who underſtand both languages, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <q>
                  <l>Coronog fab-Anne a tynir I danneth</l>
                  <l>O weilod lhoygir hid a gogleth</l>
                  <l>Vnidyn Eſchilth a gedwir un wynneth</l>
                  <l>A unnilth predaine a hunny a vith rheveth</l>
                  <l>Vn I vienglith a vernir un angalth</l>
                  <l>Vn I henaid ve lath a Bwyalth.</l>
               </q>
               <p>I ſhall endeavour howſoever to let you underſtand it, but then I muſt crave par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of my Country-men if I do it not well.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Fabanne</hi> as it is one word ſignifies a ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, ſo that <hi>Coronog fabanne</hi> thus taken, ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a Crowned Baby, which made many to expect how that it ſhould be fulfilled in K. <hi>James</hi> his time, becauſe he was crowned in his Cradle; but as you make two words
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:116046:48"/> of it, <hi>fab</hi> which ſignifies a ſon, and <hi>Anne</hi> the proper name of a woman, <hi>Coronog fab Anne,</hi> ſignifies the Crowned ſon of <hi>Anne;</hi> King <hi>Charles</hi> whoſe two elder Brethren were never Crowned: this Crowned ſon is propheſied to have his teeth pull'd out of his head, or to be lead by the teeth (for as I take it, the <hi>Welch</hi> bears both ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions) all the Kindom over, or from the center to the uttermoſt circumferences thereof: This Crowned ſon, this Prophet tels us, ſhall be at firſt, or in his younger years, deemed to be none of the wiſeſt, but in his latter years, <hi>ve lath a bwyalth,</hi> which is an expreſſion ſo copious and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigmatical, for it deciphers him and his condition ſeveral wayes, and may be taken in ſeveral kinds, for firſt it ſignifies a man that is, and as we commonly ſay, a no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table kil-cow, or a man that bears down all before him with the weight of his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument and acuteneſs of wit, like a man that laies about him with a battlear bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing down all before him, or elſe it ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fies otherwiſe, and the words wil bear the ſence as well, <hi>ve lath a Bwyalth,</hi> that is, he ſhall be ſlain with an Ax.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="86" facs="tcp:116046:49"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. XLII.</head>
               <p>THe time being come, that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſie of <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Windſor</hi> muſt now fit the fatal deſtiny of <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>Rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lan,</hi> (like a Thunder-bolt that ſplits down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, from the higher to the lower branch of the ſame Tree) <hi>viz. that he ſhould live long and looſe all:</hi> that Garriſon had the honour to make good the reare hope for a time, when the main body of the whole Kingdom, was quite forlorne. And in her laſt fortunate and ſuccesful ſally, (like a dying taper) to make one great blaze be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhe went out. In which exploit, ſome of her Gentlemen, were ſo gallant, as to bring home, (as Trophies of her Victories) colours, which were no ſooner unſhrivel'd, but they ſpread (together with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves) the praiſes of their takers; theſe being preſented to the Marqueſs, he turned away his face: ſaying, <hi>theſe are no natural colours: they are but borrowed,</hi> intimating how unnatural the war was, and how ſoon theſe colours muſt be reſtor'd.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:116046:49"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. XLIII.</head>
               <p>THere was a young and beautiful Lady, who was ſhowing the Marqueſs that the colours that hung upon ſuch a Tower, was one of the Curtains of her bed. To which my Lord reply'd, <hi>Madam: I would you would ſet the little boy, (that uſes to ſtand behind that Curtain) on the top of that Tower. That we may ſee, whether or no, he would drive away all thoſe men with his Bow and Arrowes:</hi> to which the Lady reply'd, <hi>Cupid</hi> never rais'd a ſiedge in his life; but he hath taken many a ſtrong-hold, then ſaid the Marqueſs, <hi>I will tell you how you ſhall make yours impregnable,</hi> how my Lord? (ſaid the Lady,) the Marqueſs ſaid unto her, <hi>whenſoever you ſee a handſome young man be ſure you ſhut your eyes or elſe he will take the fort of your Virginity, flying in at your windowes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. XLIV.</head>
               <p>THere was an old Servant of my Lords, who would needs make a young Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, and at laſt took an opportunity, to ſhew himſelf an arrant Coward; this Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain upon a time was to command a party
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:116046:50"/> to go out, to make a mock-ſally, but as ſoone as ever he came within ſight of the enemy, he ſquatted upon his belly, behind the refuſe of an old Brick-kill, for which his behaviour, he was laughed at ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently, after that he came into the Caſtle: ſome there were who told this unto the <hi>Marqueſs,</hi> who (being willing to bring his old Servant off, with better credit, then he had brought off himſelf) told the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers, <hi>I thought I had heard you ſay, that it was a mock-ſally,</hi> to which they an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered that it was ſo, <hi>then</hi> (ſaid the <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs,) if it was but a mock-ſally, he can be but a mock-coward, if you had bin in earneſt, it may be, he would not have plaid the foole.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. XLV.</head>
               <p>THere was a <hi>Roman</hi> Catholike who had bin converted to the Proteſtant Religion (and giving the <hi>Marqueſs</hi> of <hi>Worceſter</hi> a viſit) the <hi>Marqueſs</hi> queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on'd him (very ſeriouſly) concerning his <hi>revolt,</hi> and <hi>the ground of his deſertion,</hi> the convertite told him that the ground of his departure from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> was, becauſe ſhe had departed from her ſelf. <hi>You ſay very well,</hi> (ſaid the <hi>Marqueſs)</hi>
                  <pb n="89" facs="tcp:116046:50"/> 
                  <hi>but how do you prove that?</hi> to which demand the convertite made this reply, <hi>viz.</hi> The Scriptures tell me ſo: whereupon the <hi>Marqueſs</hi> called for a Bible, giving com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand it ſhould be a Bible <hi>Cum privilegie Regis,</hi> which being brought unto him, he ſaid unto the Gentleman <hi>I will ſee whether it will tell me any ſuch thing,</hi> and (holding it in his hands a pretty while) at laſt he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened the Bible, and held it open as long: then, he proteſted unto the foreſaid Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, that the Bible told him no ſuch matter, and that he believed it to be ſo full of truth and ſincerity, and that it reſpected the ſalvation of mens ſouls ſo much, that if there were any ſuch thing, it would (in charity (with which it was ſo fully fraught) do no leſs then acquaint him alſo with it: to which the Gentleman re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply'd; my Lord, it is not the letter, cover, or paper, that tels me ſo, it is the ſence and meaning, <hi>I cry you mercy</hi> (ſaid the <hi>Marqueſs,) who ſhall be judge of that mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, you or I?</hi> to whom the Gentleman gave his Lordſhip this anſwer, he who comes neareſt to the truth. <hi>Then</hi> (ſaid the <hi>Marq:) how ſhall we know who comes neareſt the truth?</hi> we ſhall know that (ſaid the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman) by the word it ſelf; <hi>I have told you</hi>
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:116046:51"/> (ſaid the Marqueſs) <hi>that the word it ſelf ſaies nothing<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> then (ſaid the Gentleman) there is a perſwaſive ſpirit, that directs eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, and <hi>leads them into all truth,</hi> who are ſeekers of her, meerely for love of her ſelf, <hi>Indeed</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſs) <hi>I have heard of ſuch a Sect that is newly ſprung up, which go under the name of Seekers, but I had rather be on the finders ſide;</hi> to which the Gentleman made anſwer, <hi>Seek and ye ſhall find;</hi> to which my Lord reply'd, <hi>you muſt have day-light or candle-light, or elſe your own eyes will do you no good;</hi> the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man made anſwer, that <hi>Chriſt</hi> was ſo eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to be found of all that ſought him, that if we did but groap after him we ſhould find him: I (ſaid the Marqueſs) <hi>You ſay well, but not when there is a light in the room:</hi> and thereupon the Marquels entred into a large diſcourſe, perſwading the Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man to return to his Mother again, whoſe armes were alwayes open, ready to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace all that ſhould return into her bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, to whom the Gentleman thus ſpake: my Lord, if I ſhould turn now, I ſhall be deſpiſed on all ſides, by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants, becauſe I have left them: by the Papiſts, becauſe I ſometimes left them too, and they will repoſe no confidence in me hereafter, fearing that I may do the like
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:116046:51"/> again: O (ſaid the Marqueſs) <hi>if that be all, then all is nothing,</hi> for what can any man ſay more to you then thus? <hi>you have been abroad, and you are come home again.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. XLVI.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Marqueſs</hi> had a Daughter whoſe mind gave her to be a <hi>Nun,</hi> thinking to make choice of ſuch alover as no way regarded any bodies imperfections ſo the mind was ſtreight, the <hi>Marq;</hi> fearing that ſhe might ground her reſolutions upon this diſcontent, told her, Daughter, if thou runn'ſt thy head into a <hi>Nunnery,</hi> becauſe thy ſhoulder is a little out, I'le ſtrike it in with a bagge of money, that ſhall make thee as ſtreight as any of thy Siſters; but if thou doſt wedde thy ſelf out of pure af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to thy Saviour, I ſhall think my ſelf happier in thee, then in all my Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren beſides, that he thought me worthy of being Father unto ſuch a Child, that ſhould dedicate her ſelf ſo wholly unto <hi>Chriſt:</hi> She asked her Father how much he would have given her in marriage, if ſhe had otherwiſe reſolved, and ſhould marry to his liking, telling him, that ſhe did not aske him that
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:116046:52"/> queſtion, becauſe ſhe had any ſuch thoughts in her, but that the husband to whom ſhe had vow'd her ſelf a ſpouſe, ſhould take notice of what profers ſhe had refuſed for his ſake; by this meanes the <hi>Marq;</hi> told her not with the leaſt, then ſaid ſhe unto her Father; Sir, I am going where I ſhall never ſee you more, nor ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ask you for any thing hereafter: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I beſeech you to grant me this one requeſt, which is: that the portion which you were willing to give me, if I ſhould marry, you will not grudge me as my dower, to bring to ſuch a husband, who is my Lord and Saviour: the <hi>Marq;</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving himſelf caught, gets out of the gin in this manner, <hi>Daughter</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>the huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band you talk of, will make you a very fair joynture without any portion at all but your ſelf, he wants no money; give him your heart, and he is ſatisfied.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. XLVII.</head>
               <p>THe <hi>Marqueſs</hi> had taken a new Servant to wait upon him, who had the ill luck, to think himſelf wiſer then he was thought by others, in ſo much, that upon an occaſion, he told the <hi>Manqueſs,</hi> that he was not wiſe in ſuch a thing, and that
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:116046:52"/> if he were as the <hi>Marqueſs,</hi> he would do ſo and ſo, the <hi>Marq;</hi> hearing him, made him this gentle reply, <hi>Truly if I knew where to find a Servant that were wiſer then his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, I would give gold for ſuch a one; but to have a Servant that thinks himſelf wiſer then his Maſter, I would not give a ruſh: and therefore Sir, I pray provide for your ſelf, for you are not for my turn,</hi> and ſo diſmis'd him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="48" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. XLVIII.</head>
               <p>MY Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> of <hi>Raglan</hi> (eldeſt Son to the <hi>Marq;</hi>) came into <hi>Raglan</hi> Caſtle, attended with 40 or 50 Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers, and Commanders: and his buſineſs with his Father being about procuring from the old man more money for the King, the L. <hi>Herbert</hi> in his requeſt unto his Father, (unhappily and unawares) chanced to uſe the word <hi>muſt:</hi> which his Father (the <hi>Marqueſs)</hi> laying hold on, asked him, <hi>muſt you? I pray take it,</hi> and threw him the keyes of his Treaſury, out of his pocket: whereat his Son was won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derfully out of countenance, and abaſht, (being otherwiſe ever a dutiful and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectful Son to his <hi>Father)</hi> reply'd; Sir, the word was out before I was aware, I do
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:116046:53"/> not intend to put it in force, I pray will you put up your key again: To which the <hi>Marqueſs</hi> returned his Son theſe words, <hi>Truly Son, I ſhall think my keyes not ſafe in my pocket, whilſt you have ſo many Swords by your ſides, nor that I have the Command of my houſe, whilſt you have ſo many Officers in it, nor that I am at my own diſpoſe, whilſt you have ſo many Commanders.</hi> My Lord (reply'd the Son,) I do not intend that they ſhall ſtay in the Caſtle, I mean they ſhall be gone: <hi>I pray let them</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſs,) <hi>and have a care that</hi> muſt <hi>do not ſtay behind.</hi> Whereat (after that my Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> was gone out of the room) there were ſome who (as mannerly as they could) blam'd the Marqueſs for his too much ſeverity to his Son, after that he had ſeen him expreſs ſo much of ſorrow for that over ſlip; whereupon the Marqueſs reply'd, <hi>Harke ye, if my Son be dejected, I can raiſe him when I pleaſe; but it is a queſtion if he ſhould once take a head, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I could bring him lower when I liſt:</hi> Ned <hi>was not wont to uſe ſuch courtſhip to me, and I believe he intended a better word, for his Father; but</hi> muſt <hi>was for the</hi> King.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:116046:53"/>
               <head>APOPHTH. XLIX.</head>
               <p>MY Lord <hi>Herbert,</hi> after that he had ſufficiently exhauſted his Father, by all the meanes he could poſſibly uſe, for his Majeſties relief, and had taken up all his Fathers moneys far and near, where he could either prevail with force or argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; he chanced to hear of a ſum of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney to the value of 6000l. which the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs had committed to the Lord <hi>John</hi> (his Son) his care &amp; truſty preſervation abroad; this money, my Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> happened to hear of, and acquaints the King there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with, ingaging the King in the buſineſs, and tells the King, that if he would ſend for his brother the Lord <hi>John,</hi> to come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and would ſay but thus and thus unto him, that he would undertake, he might have the 6000 l. the <hi>Kings</hi> occaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons were then urgent (being then before <hi>Gloceſter,</hi> &amp; hard pinch'd for lack of mony) through My Lord <hi>Herberts</hi> perſwaſion, my Lord <hi>John</hi> was ſent for, came; and the buſineſs took effect, the <hi>King</hi> promiſing to repay it by ſuch a time: when time and ſuſpition perſwaded the Marqueſs to call in this money; excuſes made delaies for a time, but at laſt all excuſes
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:116046:54"/> being ſet apart, by importunity: the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs wiſht his Son <hi>John</hi> to go and fetch the money, or elſe never to ſee his face a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more; part of which injunction the Lord <hi>John</hi> performed, but never the other. Not long after the Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> coming to his Father, his Father receiv'd him with wonted (but unexpected) chearfulneſs: it ſo happened that my Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to excuſe himſelf unto his Father, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this buſineſs; on whom the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther beſtowed this language: <hi>Son, I pray ſave your ſelf the labour, for I do not blame you at all, neither am I angry with you; for I never truſted you with the money: I love no man the worſe for following his profeſſion; and you have made it your profeſſion (all along) to deceive your Father, to help the</hi> King, <hi>but I do not love a man that will take away another mans profeſſion from him, and deceive his own Father of his money, and his brother of his calling.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="apothegm">
               <head>APOPHTH. L.</head>
               <p>WHen it was told the Marqueſs that ſome would warrant him, that if he would, he might be Duke of <hi>Somerſet;</hi> he made them this reply: <hi>When I was Earl of</hi> Worceſter, <hi>I was well to live: ſince I was a
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:116046:54"/> Matqueſs I am worſe by one hundred thouſand pound, and if I ſhould be a Duke, I ſhould be an arrant beggar: Wherefore I had rather (if I might) go back again to my Earldome, then at this rate keep on my pace, to the Dukedome of</hi> Sommerſet.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="apothegm">
               <head>APO. LI.</head>
               <p>AT the beginning of this Parliament, there were certain ruſticks who came unto <hi>Raglan</hi> Caſtle, to ſearch the Caſtle for Armes, my Lord being a Papiſt, the Marqueſs met them at the gate, and with a ſtern countenance, demanded of them what they would have: they ſomewhat daunted at his preſence, told his Lordſhip that they were come to ſearch his houſe for Armes, the Marqueſs told them, <hi>ſurely no, they were come to take the Castle, and all that was in it;</hi> they told him not, then he ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, <hi>why they did diſarm him, if they did not intend to take away his money,</hi> they ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was a Recuſant, the Marqueſs told them, <hi>that he was a Peer of the Realm, and no convict Recuſant, and therefore the Law could not in reaſon take notice of any ſuch thing,</hi> and demanded of them, <hi>whether or no they had been in any ſuch authority before?</hi> they anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:116046:55"/> no: <hi>then</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſſe with a loud voice) Ile make you before I go hence—and (as if ſome deſperate and cautious reſolution had kept back ſome words which might have diſcovered ſome deſign before that he had brought them to the place of execution) there making a ſtop, calling upon them to <hi>come along;</hi> The fillie people amaz'd and full of horrour hung back, and asked the Marqueſſe, what my Lord? what will you make us do? <hi>ſhew your Commiſſion</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſſe) they glad it was no worſe, told the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſſe that they were ſatisfied, <hi>but I am not ſatisfied</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſſe) <hi>for now you are come you ſhall ſearch,</hi> if your Lordſhip will have us ſearch (ſaid the ſearchers) we will, but otherwiſe we will take your word. <hi>O I thank you heartily</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſſe) <hi>but pray come along;</hi> they followed him, but knew not what to think on't, nor what ſhould become of them following the Marqueſs, as if they had deſir'd that his Lordſhip ſhould have ſhown them the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, rather then as if they went with any authority to ſearch for any Armes that were there, the Marqueſs ſtill asking them if they had a mind to ſearch <hi>here</hi> or <hi>there,</hi> they ſtill anſwering his Lordſhip, no, no,
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:116046:55"/> my Lord, we know you mean no hurt, ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver asking him which was the way to the Armoury or the like, at length the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs brought them over the high bridge that archt over the moat that was between the Caſtle and the great Tower, wherein the Lord <hi>Herbert</hi> had newly contriv'd cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain water-works, which when the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral engins and wheels were to be ſet a going; much quantity of water through the hollow conveyances of the <hi>aquaeducts,</hi> were to be let down from the top of the high Tower, which upon the firſt entrance of theſe wonderfull Aſinegoes; the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs had given order that theſe cataracts ſhould begin to fall, which made ſuch a fearful and hideous noiſe, by reaſon of the hollowneſſe of the Tower, and the neighbouring ecchoes of the Caſtle, and the waters that were between and round them both, that there was ſuch a roaring, as if the mouth of hell had been wide open and all the devils had bin conjur'd up, that the poor ſilly men ſtood ſo amaz'd, as if they had been half dead, and yet they ſaw nothing; at laſt as the plot was laid, up comes a man ſtaring and running, crying out before he came at us, look to your ſelves my maſters, for the Lions are all
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:116046:56"/> got looſe; whereupon the ſearchers gave us ſuch a looſe, that they tumbled ſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver one another down the ſtairs, that we thought one half of them had broken their neeks, never looking behinde them, till they were ſure they had got out of ſight of the Caſtle.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="apothegm">
               <head>APO. LII.</head>
               <p>WHen General <hi>Fairfax</hi> came into the Leaguer before <hi>Raglan,</hi> and had ſent us Propoſitions, wherein all the Officers and Souldiers were offered fair conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, but none at all for the Marqueſs: we thinking it a thing ſo unanſwerable and diſhonourable in our own opinions, as to deliver it upon ſuch conditions, were reſolved to ſtand it out, to the laſt; which reſolution of ours, begat in us an expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of a ſtorm; which expectation of ours, was improv'd, by ſome intelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence which we had to that purpoſe: which the Marqueſs having notice of, call'd all his Officers before him, and made this Speech unto them.</p>
               <p>
                  <q>Gentlemen, I have ſomewhat to ſay to you, which it may be you may take for a complement; but this is no time
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:116046:56"/> for complement: I underſtand that you expect (this night) to be ſtorm'd; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have called you before me; and do make it my ſuit unto you, that ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then this ſtorm ſhould be raiſed for my ſake, onely (which muſt be ſo, ſeeing that you are all offered large Articles for your ſelves) that I may be the <hi>Jonas</hi> to be caſt over board, rather then that ye all ſhould periſh; for I have but a little old, and cold blood running in my veines, which is not worth the effuſion of ſo much precious and youthfull blood, as is running in yours: and therefore you ſhall do me a pleaſure, and your ſelves a benefit if you grant me my requeſt:</q> To which it was anſwered by all, that the tearmes were not <hi>honourable,</hi> whereat the Marqueſs reply'd;</p>
               <p>
                  <q>
                     <hi>Non ponebat enim rumores ante ſalutem,</hi> was the maxime of a Souldier as much as any thing;</q> but being denied his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, the Officers all told him, that they would all dye to a man, but they would have like Artiles for him, as for themſelves: to which in mild tearms and Princely gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vity, he told them: <hi>I do not like that way of imbalming, neither to be ſerv'd up to my eternity, as a thing newly taken out of the ſowſe of ſo many friends blood.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="102" facs="tcp:116046:57"/>
               <head>APO. LIII.</head>
               <p>WHen the Gariſon was ſurrendred and the Generall had entred the Caſtle, the Marqueſſe met him in the Hall, and (asking which was he) the Marqueſs ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted him thus: <hi>Sir, I hear you are a man of you word, that was it that took the Caſtle: other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, had you been never ſo tall a man of your hands, you ſhould have ſtay'd a little while longer, before we had bid you welcome:</hi> the Generall told his Lordſhip, that knowing him to be a man of honour, he thought him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf oblig'd to make that journey, on pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to ſee his Lordſhip fairly dealt with, according to Articles, and to be delivered into civil hands: the Marqueſs reply'd, <hi>I thank you for your curteſie, but I wiſh that you had let it alone untill ſome other time, for there was no haſte.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="apothegm">
               <head>APO. LIV.</head>
               <p>AFter much Conference between the Marqueſs and the General, wherein many things were requeſted of the General by the Marqueſs, and being (as he thought himſelf) happy in the obtainment, his
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:116046:57"/> Lordſhip was pleaſed to make a merry Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tition unto the General, as he was taking his leave, <hi>viz.</hi> in the behalf of a couple of pigeons which were wont to come to his hand, and feed out of it conſtantly: in whoſe behalf he deſired the General; that he would be pleaſed to give him his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection for them, fearing the little com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that he ſhould have over his Soul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers in that behalf, to which the General ſaid, I am glad to ſee your Lordſhip ſo merry: <hi>O</hi> (ſaid the Marqueſs) <hi>you have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven me no other cauſe, and as haſty as you are, you ſhall not go, untill I have told you a story. There were two men going up</hi> Holborn <hi>in a cart to be hang'd, one of them being very merry and jocund, gave offence unto the other, who was as ſad and dejected, in ſo much as that the down-caſt man ſaid unto the other, I wonder brother you can be ſo frolick, conſidering the buſineſſe we are going about: tuſh anſwered the other, thou art a fool, thou went'ſt a theeving, &amp; never thought'ſt what would become of thee: wherefore being all of a ſuddain ſurpriz'd, thou fallest into ſuch a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t, that I am aſhamed to ſee thee in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, whereas I was reſolv'd to be hang'd, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ever I fell to ſtealing, which is the reaſon, that (nothing happening ſtrange or unexpected) I go ſo compos'd unto my death. So</hi> (ſaid the
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:116046:58"/> Marqueſs) <hi>I reſolv'd to undergo whatſoever (even the worſt of evil) you were able to lay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on me, before ever I took up Armes for my Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign; and therefore wonder not that I am ſo merry.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="55" type="apothegm">
               <head>APO. LV.</head>
               <p>THere was a Colonel (whoſe civility in other reſpects, deſerves to have his name unmentioned) who came unto the Marqueſs (after the Caſtle was delivered) at the firſt as not remembering himſelf a Conquerour, whom the Marqueſs recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving as not forgetting himſelf to be Lord of <hi>Raglan,</hi> untill ſuch time as the Colonel deſired reparation of certain loſſes which he had ſuſtained by his ſon <hi>Glamorgan,</hi> the Marqueſs <hi>pray'd him not to call him to account for other folkes, for he had enough to do to anſwer for himſelf:</hi> hereat the Colonel clapt his hat upon his head, and ſate himſelf down in a chair of State, which was upon my Lords right hand, which the Marqueſs ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving, gently ſaid unto one of his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, <hi>I pray reach him the footſtool.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="56" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="105" facs="tcp:116046:58"/>
               <head>APO. LVI.</head>
               <p>WHen the Marqueſs of <hi>Worcester</hi> was brought up to <hi>London,</hi> and was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the Black-rod, he asked me, now what have they done with me? I anſwered, they have committed your Lordſhip to the Black-rod, his Lordſhip preſently made me this reply: <hi>I had rather be under the Black<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rod, then under a black cloud.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="57" type="apothegm">
               <head>APO. LVII.</head>
               <p>WHen it was told his Lordſhip not ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hours before he dyed, that leave was obtained by the Parliament, that he might be buried in <hi>Windſor</hi> Caſtle: (where there is a peculiar for the family) within the great Chappel, and wherein divers of his Anceſtors lies buried) with ſome ſprightlineſſe he ſpake aloud, <hi>God bleſs us all! why then I ſhall take a better Castle when I am dead, then they took from me whileſt I was alive.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="58" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="106" facs="tcp:116046:59"/>
               <head>APO. LVIII.</head>
               <p>A Little before he dyed, lie fell into many heavenly ejaculations, and Divine ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures (as thoſe who knew him b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt, knew thoſe things to be but ordinary with him, and therefore no wonder that they would not leave him, till death had ſet Divine meditations to cloſe his eyes) and in that intervall of deaths pangs (which we uſe to call a lightning before death) he hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened (as if his pious ſoul (like a candle going out) had made one great blaze) to ſpeak theſe words a little before he dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to thoſe who were about him. <hi>I pray rejoyce with me you that love me, and thank God for it: I have my liberty, my health, and my deliverance, from all mine enemies grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed unto me:</hi> and thereupon he pauſed, as if he expected (ſome body to ſpeak to him, which being underſtood by one who was neareſt unto him, he asked, how ſo my Lord? to which he returned this anſwer, <hi>My ſoul ſhall ſhortly have her liberty from the priſon of my body, my health ſhall be my ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and the riddance of mine enemies, ſhall be my Saviours deliverance from all my ſins;</hi> and thereupon he fell into a kind of laugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:116046:59"/> ſuch an one as might become a dying man, tranſported with inward joy, and entring into his triumph over death, and ſaid, <hi>Lord bleſs us, what a fearfull thing was this Black-rod? when I heard of it first: it did ſo run in my minde, that it made an affliction out of mine own imaginations: but when I ſpoke with the man, I found him a very civil Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, but I ſaw no Black-rod; ſo if we would not let theſe troubles and adverſities of ours, be made worſe by our own apprehenſions, no Rods would be black.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="59" type="apothegm">
               <head>APO. LIX.</head>
               <p>I Had procured for the Marqueſs of <hi>Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter</hi> (being a Commiſſioner for the ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>render of <hi>Raglan</hi> Caſtle) theſe Articles in his behalf, <hi>viz.</hi> that he ſhould have his li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to march and ſail away with all his goods and neceſſaries to any part of land beyond the Seas, and that he ſhould have under the Generals hand, paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes granted unto him, both by Land and Sea, with carts by Land, and waftage by Sea, and Convoies by both, paying the ordinary rates, and that in regard that he was an excepted man, a ceſſation from arms and work was agreed upon for ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:116046:60"/> dayes, in which time an Ordinance of Parliament was to be obtain'd for the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification of the foreſaid Articles; but it ſeemes the Marqueſs had let ſome inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ations of the enemy, batter his wiſdome, where it lay not ſo well fortified as it ſhould be, againſt ſo prevailing an enemy as covetouſneſſe, for if he had any fault it was that, and if any weakneſſe it was that, which was rather incident to his age then him, ſuſpition, theſe two agreed very well together (like fire and charcole that makes a moſt excellent fire to conſume themſelves) and deſtroy the ſubject of their reſidence, <hi>in quo quis peccat in eo puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur,</hi> beware of covetouſneſſe and ſuſpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your friends, for this wiſe man loſt himſelf, and made ſhipwrack of his wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, even in the Harbour after ſo long a voyage as threeſcore and ſixteen years toſſement upon the waves of this trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome world, and loſt ſo great a bottome, and ſo goodly a fraught, as <hi>Raglan</hi> and all that was within her, out of a meer itching humour of getting in with that very tide: for it was that faction (that common diſeaſe that had ſpread it ſelf through all the parts of the Kings Army) had now play'd his laſt prize, ſo that the ears that
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:116046:60"/> had let in ſo much wiſdom all along, were now at laſt ſtopt with poyſon ſo, that he could not hearken unto the adviſe of his beſt friends, after that the ſubtile inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of his worſt enemies had perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him to acts tending to his own ruine and deſtruction, for (the place appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for the Treaty being at one <hi>Oates</hi> his houſe, a place indifferent between <hi>Raglan</hi> Caſtle, and the General <hi>Fairfax</hi> his Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters then at <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ske)</hi> the Marqueſs of <hi>Worceſter</hi> had caus'd a ſpie to creep into ſuch a part of the houſe appointed for the Treaty, that he might ſuperviſe and hear all our words and actions (being drawn thereunto ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by profer'd ſervice then cauſe of jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie) whereby inſinuation had now got ſome advantage of ground whereon to place its engine, for this fellow after that we had concluded upon the fore-ſaid Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles (with much inſiſtance) the Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oners for the General as their laſt arrow, chanced to ſhoot this unlucky ſhaft which hit the mark they aim'd at, for they deſired us notwithſanding al theſe procurements, that we would perſwade my Lord to throw himſelf upon the mercy of the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament, and that if he would do ſo it ſhould be better for him, and that the Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:116046:61"/> ſhould mediate for him in his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half, that he might have ſome allowance out of his Eſtate, whereby he might live like himſelf; alſo there was an overture of a Petition to be drawn by the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the County in his behalf, which ſhould declare unto the Parliament how little hoſtility he had uſed until ſuch time as he was provoked within the pales of his own Park, and that he never gathered any Contribution from the Country, but paid the Souldiers of his Gariſon out of his privy purſe, &amp;c. all which and more they might very juſtly have done, if it had bin poſſible they could have been ſo honeſt; the truth whereof made the poor Marqueſs the more confident of the reality: all this we thought not fit to acquaint the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs with upon our return, leſt deluſion ſhould get into that ear that was too o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen for ſuch a reception, and peſter and infect the clearneſs of his judgement with the evaporation of an apple out of <hi>Pale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine:</hi> the non-performance whereof, this man makes to the Marqueſs, a failing of truſt, and a falling ſhort of duty in us, and withall, puts a jealouſie into the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſs of his own childrens, and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, reſolution to carry him away by
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:116046:61"/> virtue of theſe Articles, and then to uſe him as they liſted, and do wirh him what they pleaſed, and therefore it were better for him to throw himſelf upon the Parliament, who cannot poſſibly be ſo unreaſonable as not to let him have what he might have had without them, whatſoever more that he was ſure of, to diſpoſe of as he liſt: and all this was to the end, that if he could cauſe diſtruſt to be given to his own children and his faithful friends, he and ſuch as he ſhould have the ſecret conveyance of moſt of his money, plate and jewels, which they had; for the Marqueſs following their councels, threw himſelf upon the mercy of the Parliament, which was no other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe then as is before related, which being once done, the truſtees never ſaw his Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip more, but ſent him word that they were bound in Bonds for his ſons in as much as that came unto, and now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hey had the means in their hands, they would ſave themſelves harmleſſe: Thus Kings may be loſt by their too much goodneſſe, and wiſe-men may be overthrown by over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſdome, the Marqueſs by ſuch hard uſage on all ſides, being brought ſo near his end, asked us <hi>what was the name of the</hi>
                  <pb n="112" facs="tcp:116046:62"/> 
                  <hi>place where they had brought him,</hi> it was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered <hi>Covengarden,</hi> he demanded of us, <hi>what we thought of Fortune-tellers?</hi> it was an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, that ſome of them ſpake ſhrewdly: <hi>It was told me</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>by ſome of them before ever I was a Catholike, that I ſhould dye in a Covent, but I never believed him before; yet I hope you will not bury me in a garden:</hi> and directing his ſpeech to me in particular, he deſired me that I <hi>would go to the Generall and tell him how it was with him, and that now he was not in a condition of deſiring any earthly favour, or making uſe of any humane mercy, yet in regard that the General had engaged himſelf in ſome particulars concerning him, which he was confident he did perform on his part, but was a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſed in that the bare Articles of the ſurrender of his houſe were only delivered into the Parliament and not his letter, which ſhould have ſignified the Articles which he waved, throwing himſelf upon their mercy, that he would be pleaſed to have ſome reſpect unto his own honour, lest that ſhould ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with him, and that he would certifie the houſe of Lords how ill he had been uſed, and that their favours might reach to that if it went no further, that he might dye a freeman.</hi> I did this meſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuage to the General, whom I found touch'd with a ſence of true Nobility, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting thoſe falſe dealings, and ſorrowing
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:116046:62"/> for his Lordſhips hard uſage, both which procured from him, a Letter to the Houſe of Peers, which teſtified unto them the truth of all the particulars required; which Letter was read in the Houſe, but all the mercy or juſtice it procured to the Marqueſs, or reſpect to the General, was, that they carped at the Generals writing unto them, and not coming himſelf being he was in Town: and wondring that he ſhould offer to call him Marqueſs and not Earl of <hi>Worceſter,</hi> &amp; ſo flung off all further conſiderations with this only ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; that they knew as much before: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let no man pitty their fall, though their Lordſhips were al ſet up like ſo many dumb ſtatues in the Houſe of Commons; but when the Marqueſs had an account of all the paſſages, <hi>O</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>when the nobleſt &amp; higheſt element courts the noiſe of the waves, the truest Emblem of the madneſs of the people, and when the higheſt region ſtoops unto the low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and the lowest gets up into the higheſt ſeat, what can be expected but a Chaos of confuſion and diſſolution of the univerſe? I do believe that they are ſo near unto their end, that as weak as I am there is Phyſick to be had, if a man gold find, to prolong my days, that I might out-live their honours.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="60" type="apothegm">
               <pb n="114" facs="tcp:116046:63"/>
               <head>APO. LX.</head>
               <p>A Little before he died (reflecting upon the Articles which he had wav'd, upon the ſurrender of <hi>Raglan</hi> into the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments hands) <hi>Ah Doctor</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>if I had made uſe of thoſe Articles which you had procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in my behalf, I had not been now ſo near un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the end of my life, &amp; the beginning of my hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſs: I for ſook life, liberty and eſtate (which I might have had) and threw my ſelf upon their mercy; which when I had done, if, to ſeize up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all my goods, to pull down my houſe, to ſell my eſtate, and to ſend for up, ſuch a weak body as mine was, ſo enfeebled by diſeaſes, in the dead of Winter, and the winter of mine Age, be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull; what are they whoſe mercies are ſo cruell? neither do I expect that they ſhould ſtop at all this; for I fear that they will perſecute me after death. You tell me (that when I am dead) you will petition the Parliament for money to bury me; then will they appoint thoſe, who will diſpoſe of the time, and manner of my Buriall; and you ſhall ſee, that they (being it is ſo near this good time) will cauſe me to be buried according to the Directory:</hi> In ſpight of <hi>Chriſtmas</hi> day: upon <hi>Chriſtmas,</hi> and ſo they did.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:116046:63"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
